<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Advanced Scheduler Settings">
	<header1>
	Advanced Scheduler Settings
</header1>
	<ul>
		<li>
			When <i>Enable Refresh</i> is checked (on), redrawing is limited 
			to the rate set by the <i>Refresh Rate</i> parameter.
		</li>
		<li><i>Event Interval</i> is the rate, in milliseconds, at which 
			Max services the low-priority queue, which includes redrawing 
			the screen. The effective rate of redrawing is limited by 
			the <i>Refresh Interval</i>, but other, less expensive low-priority 
			events may occur more often. The default value of is 2 ms.
		</li>
		<li>
			When <i>Overdrive</i> is enabled, Max gives priority to timing and 
			MIDI processing over screen drawing and user interface tasks such as 
			responding to mouse clicks. If you are primarily going to be using Max 
			for MIDI or audio processing, Overdrive should be enabled. If you are 
			primarily going to be using Jitter, Overdrive should be disabled. 
			In addition, the debugging features of Max only work if overdrive is 
			disabled.
		</li>
		<li><i>Poll Throttle</i> sets the number of high-priority 
			events processed per by the scheduler at one time. High 
			priority events include MIDI as well as events generated 
			by <o>metro</o> and other timing objects. A lower setting 
			(e.g., 1) means less event clumping, while a higher value 
			(e.g., 100) will result in less of an event backlog. The 
			default value is 20 events.
		</li>
		<li><i>Queue Throttle</i> sets the number of events processed 
			per servicing of the low priority event queue (Low priority 
			events include user interface events, graphics operations, 
			reading files from disk, and other expensive operations that 
			would otherwise cause timing problems for the scheduler). A 
			lower setting (e.g. 1) means less event clumping, while a 
			higher value (e.g. 100) will result in less of an event backlog. 
			The default value is 10 events.
		</li>
		<li><i>Redraw Queue Throttle</i> sets the maximum number of patcher
			UI update events to process at a time. Lower values can lead
			to more processing power being made available to other low-priority
			Max processes, and higher values make user interfaces more responsive
			(especially for patches in which large numbers of <o>bpatcher</o>
			objects are being used). The default value is 1000 ms.
		</li>
		<li><i>Refresh Rate</i> sets the minimum time, in milliseconds, 
			between updating of the interface. A lower setting (e.g., 5) 
			means that Max will devote more time to redrawing the screen 
			and less to responding to user input, while a higher value (e.g., 60) 
			will mean that the interface is faster and more responsive. The 
			default value is 33.3 ms. This setting has no effect unless <i>Enable Refresh</i> 
			is checked.
		</li>
		<li><i>Scheduler Interval</i> sets the interval, in milliseconds, 
				between timer ticks. This determines how often the scheduler 
				services events when <i>Overdrive</i> is enabled. This setting 
				can range from 1 to 20 ms. Larger intervals can dramatically 
				reduce overall CPU utilization at the expense of timing accuracy. 
				The default value is 1 ms.
		</li>
		<li><i>Scheduler slop</i> is the amount of time, in milliseconds, the 
			scheduler is permitted to fall behind actual time before correcting 
			the scheduler time to actual time. The scheduler will fall behind 
			actual time if there are more high priority events than the computer 
			can process. Typically some amount of slop is desired so that 
			high priority events will maintain long term temporal accuracy 
			despite small temporal deviations. A lower setting (e.g., 1) results 
			in greater short term accuracy, while a higher value (e.g., 100) 
			will mean that the scheduler is more accurate in the long term. 
			The default value is 25 milliseconds.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<br/>
</vignette>
