<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Assistance Settings">
	<header1>
	Setting Assistance preferences
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Assistance</i> category of the Max Preferences window
			shows the settings associated with using the 
			<link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Assistance</link>
			features of Max that allow you to get hints about what kinds of messages or data the inlets
			and outlets of an object will receive or send. 
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="enableassistance"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Setting your Assistance preference
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) to show the Preferences Window. 
			Scroll to the <b>Assistance</b>
			category of the preferences listings, and click in the
			Assistance Bubbles checkbox to enable or disable Assistance bubbles.
			<br/>
			When Assistance bubbles are enabled, they will appear in the Patcher Window. When
			the Assistance Bubbles checkbox is unchecked, all Assistance information will be
			printed in the
			Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
			<br/>
			The Max application keeps track of whether or not assistance has been enabled or disabled - 
			if assistance is enabled the last time you quit the program, it will be enabled when
			you launch Max again.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bodytext>
			You can choose both the background color of the 
			<link anchor="assistancebubble" module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Assistance bubble</link> 
			and the color of the text displayed in the bubble. 
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="assistancecolors"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Changing the Assistance bubble display colors
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) 
			to show the Preferences Window, then scroll to the <b>Assistance</b> category.
			Click in the Values column for the Assistance Background Color and Assistance Text
			Color settings and use the
			<link module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">Color Picker</link>
			to change the look of the layout display (Note: these colors are used for both the assistance
			and layout bubbles).
			The Max application keeps track of this setting, and it will be used
			whenever you launch the program.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bodytext>
			By default, Max 
			<link module="core" name="help_docs" type="vignette">help files</link> 
			are only available when a patcher window is unlocked.
			You can set Max to let you access help files from a patcher window when it is
			locked.
		</bodytext>
	<a name="helpinlockedpatcher"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Enabling help files in locked Patcher windows
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) to 
			show the Preferences Window. Scroll to the <b>Assistance</b>
			category of the preferences listings, and click in the Help in Locked Patchers
			checkbox in the Preferences window. When this option is checked, you will be able to use Assistance 
			even when a Patcher window is locked. 
			The Max application keeps track of this setting, and it will be enabled or disabled
			depending on its state the last time you quit the program.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="enablelayoutbubble"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Enabling/Disabling layout bubbles
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) to show the Preferences Window. 
			Scroll to the <b>Assistance</b>
			category of the preferences listings, and click in the
			Layout Bubbles checkbox to enable or disable Layout bubbles.
			<br/>
			When Layout bubbles are enabled, they will appear in the Patcher Window. When
			the Layout Bubbles checkbox is unchecked, all Layout information will be
			printed in the Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
			<br/>
			The Max application keeps track of this setting, and it will be enabled or disabled
			depending on its state the last time you quit the program.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
			You can choose both the background color of the 
			<link anchor="layoutbubble" module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Layout bubble</link> 
			and the color of the text displayed in the bubble. 
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="layoutcolors"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Changing the layout bubble's display colors
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) 
			to show the Preferences Window.
			Scroll to the <b>Assistance</b>
			category of the preferences listings, then click in the Values column for the Assistance 
			Background Color and Assistance Text
			Color settings and use the
			<link module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">Color Picker</link>
			to change the look of the layout display (Note: these colors are used for both the layout
			and assistance bubbles).
			The Max application keeps track of this setting, and it will be used
			whenever you launch the program.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
</vignette>
