<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Inspecting Attributes">
	<header1>
	Inspecting Attributes
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
	You will encounter several different types of attributes. Each type has a 
	different "edit style" in an 
	<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link> 
	window. Note that all attribute changes are undoable by choosing <b>Undo Attribute Change</b> 
	from the Edit menu.
</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Selecting and inspecting objects
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select an object or multiple objects in your patcher window by Shift-clicking or clicking
		and dragging an outline around the objects.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click the Inspector button in the patcher toolbar.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
		When you open the object inspector on multiple objects, only the attributes 
		shared by the objects are shown.If you have selected objects of different 
		types, the Inspector window will appear with the title 
		<i>multiple objects inspector</i>. 
		In most cases, this means only the 
		<link module="core" name="attributes_stdbox" type="vignette">common box attributes</link> 
		will appear in the inspector.
	</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/inspector_12.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			<link module="core" name="font_attributes" type="vignette">Editing font attributes</link>
		</header2>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Editing basic text attributes
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Double-click in the Value column to edit the attribute
		</li>
			<li>
			Enter some text
		</li>
			<li>
			Press return or click outside the text box to store the change to the attribute
		</li>
			<li>
			If the attribute returns to its original value, it means you typed in something illegal for this attribute
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/attributes_inspecting1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Editing color attributes
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click in the Value column to open the 
			<link module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">Color Picker</link>
		</li>
			<li>
			Edit the color
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/attributes_inspecting2.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Editing menu attributes
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click in the Value column to see the pop-up menu with attribute choices
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose the new attribute value from the menu or click outside the menu to cancel
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/attributes_inspecting3.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Editing filename or folder attributes
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click the <b>Choose...</b> button to use an open file dialog to pick a file or folder.
		</li>
			<li>
			Alternatively, double-click to the right of the Choose button to enter the filename 
			directly
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/attributes_inspecting4.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Editing large text attributes
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click the <b>Edit</b> button to edit the text in a modal text editor window
		</li>
			<li>
			Alternatively, if you have a very small amount of text, double-click to the 
			right of the Edit button to enter the text directly
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/attributes_inspecting5.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Editing on/off (switch) attributes
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>Use the checkbox to turn the attribute on or off</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/attributes_inspecting6.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Editing time value attributes
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>Use pop-up menu on the right to set the units</li>
			<li>Enter the value in the text field at the left-hand side</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/attributes_inspecting7.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Working with Attribute Default Values
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select an object or objects in the Patcher window.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click in any column in an attribute's row in the Inspector
		to select it.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click on the Modify Selected Item in the Inspector toolbar
		and select an option from the pull-down menu. When you release
		the mouse button, the selected option will be applied to your
		object.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/inspector_set_attribute_to_default_value.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
		You can use the Modify Selected Item pull-down menu to perform
		several useful tasks when you are editing attributes
	</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Choosing 
		<b>Revert Value</b> from the 
		Modify Selected Item pull-down menu will return the selected 
		attribute to its previous value.
	</li>
			<li>
		Choosing 
		<b>Set to Default Value</b> from the 
		Modify Selected Item pull-down menu will set the 
		selected attribute to its default value.
	</li>
			<li>	
		Max lets you create
		<link module="core" name="ui_defaults" type="vignette">color schemes</link>
		that apply consistent color schemes to the Max patching environment.
		If you are using one of these color schemes, choosing 
		<b>Set to Named Default Value</b> from the 
		Modify Selected Item pull-down menu will return the selected attribute to the 
		default setting for the currently loaded color scheme.
	</li>
			<li>
		If you are working with 
		<link module="core" name="freezing_attributes" type="vignette">frozen attribute</link> 
		values, you can use choose 
		<b>Set to Frozen Value</b>
		from the Modify Selected Item pull-down menu to return the selected attribute to the 
		setting you used when you originally froze the attribute.
		This menu item will only be enabled if the attribute has a 
		frozen value and the current value deviates from that frozen value. 
	</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<header2>
		Keeping Track of Objects and their Attributes
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		When you're working with multiple objects that have lots of attributes
		you want to keep track of, it's sometimes difficult to keep track of
		which of the objects in your patch you're currently working with. Clicking
		on the <i>Show Object</i> button in the 
		Inspector toolbar
		will temporarily color the object you're working on for easy identification.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/inspector_show_object.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Adding an attrui Object to Your Patch
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select an object in the Patcher window.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click in any column in an attribute's row in the Inspector
		to select it.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click on the <i>Make Attribute in Patcher</i> button in the
		<link module="core" name="inspector_toolbar" type="vignette">Object Inspector toolbar</link>.
		A connected
		<o>attrui</o> object will be automatically added to your patch that
		displays the selected attribute.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/inspector_make_attribute_in_patcher.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
</vignette>
