<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Foreground and Background Layers">
	<header1>
	Foreground and Background Layers
	</header1>
<bodytext>
By default, objects you add to a patcher are in the <i>foreground layer</i>. Objects in the <i>background layer</i> appear behind all objects in the foreground layer. In addition, the background layer can be locked, so you can reposition objects in the foreground layer on top of the background without it getting in the way.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	The two layers exist in both patching and presentation modes. However, the layer an object belongs to is the same in both modes.
</bodytext>
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Moving an object to the background layer
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>Select the object you wish to place in the background layer</li>
		<li>Choose <b>Include in Background</b> from the Arrange menu. The object will now appear behind all objects in the foreground.</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Moving an object to the background layer
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>Ensure that the background layer is not locked by verifying that <b>Lock Background</b> is not checked in the View menu. If the background is locked you cannot select objects in the background layer.</li>
		<li>Select the object in the background layer you wish to move to the foreground</li>
		<li>Choose <b>Remove from Background</b> from the Arrange menu</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Locking and unlocking the background layer
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>To lock the background layer, which prevents selecting or editing of any objects it contains, check <b>Lock Background</b> in the View menu.</li>
		<li>To unlock the background layer, uncheck <b>Lock Background</b> in the View menu.</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Hiding layers
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>To hide all objects in the background layer, choose <b>Hide Background</b> from the View menu. To show the background again, choose <b>Show Background</b> from the View menu.</li>
		<li>To hide all objects in the foreground layer, choose <b>Hide Foreground</b> from the View menu. To show the foreground again, choose <b>Show Foreground</b> from the View menu.</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bodytext>
	Note that the invisibility of the background or foreground layers is only a temporary setting for editing purposes. Both layers will always be visible when you open a patcher. Hiding the foreground is useful for making changes to objects in the background without the foreground objects getting in the way.
</bodytext>

</vignette>
