<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Circular Object menu">
	<header1>
		The Circular Object Menu
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The circular object menu in Max provides a quick and easy way to patch 
			intuitively that replaces and extends the earlier
			quickref
			menu. This menu has several sub-menus that provide a means of accessing to help files, 
			reference files, and object Inspectors for an object. It also provides a quick way 
			to discover object the messages and attributes associated with that object, and
			serves as an aid to Max patching.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Viewing the circular object menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu. As you move 
			your mouse over a segment of the circular menu, a label appears to identify the
			various menus associated with the object. The number of menus shown depends upon
			the Max object you have selected
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			To hide the circular object menu, move your cursor away from the circular object 
			menu and it will disappear.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Displaying and using a sectional menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over a segment of the circular menu, click to display the
			sectional menu's contents, and drag to the menu item you want to select.
			When you hover over a menu item, you'll see a description of it appear in the
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>
			in your patcher window. When you release your mouse, the menu activity will be performed.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_2.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bodytext>
			The circular object consists of six sectional menus:
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
			The <i>Object</i> menu gives you access to general information about the selected object.
		</li>
		<li>
			The <i>Attributes</i> menu lets you discover the 
			<link module="core" name="attributes" type="vignette">attributes</link> 
			associated the the object.
		</li>
		<li>
			The <i>Prototype</i> menu will provide you with access to 
			<link module="core" name="prototypes" type="vignette">prototypes</link>
			of any user interface object you select.
		</li>
		<li>
			The <i>Preferences</i> menu lets change the size of the circular menu.
		</li>
		<li>
			The <i>Connect</i> menu displays information associated with object inlets and outlets.
		</li>
		<li>
			The <i>Messages</i> menu lets you discover the 
			messages that the selected object knows about and will respond to.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Setting the circular object menu size
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			If you find it difficult to work with the circular object menu because of
			its size, you can select a larger version of the menu to aid in your
			patching life.
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over a Preferences segment of the circular menu, click to display 
			the Preferences menu and drag to select the <b>Use Large Wheel</b> menu item. The
			next time you use the circular object menu, you'll be working with a larger version.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_9.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="circular_reference"/>
	<header1>
		Finding Out About Objects Using the Circular Object Menu
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The circular object menu provides quick and easy ways to find out about an object -
			its function, the information is receives and sends to and from other Max objects,
			and the
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="attributes" type="vignette">attributes</link>
			and messages it understands. This information is easily accessible with a couple of clicks and some mousing.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Using the circular object menu to find out about an object
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over any segment of the circular menu, click to display the
			sectional menu's contents, and drag to the examine a menu item. When you hover
			over a menu item, you'll see a description of it appear in the
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>
			in your patcher window.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_3.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Inspector</b> from the Object sectional menu and release to open the object's
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Help</b> from the Object sectional menu to open the object's
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="help_docs" type="vignette">Help files</link>.
		</li>
			<li>			
			Choose <b>Reference</b> from the Object sectional menu to open the object's
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="help_docs" type="vignette">Reference pages</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<header1>
		Max Patching Using the Circular Object Menu
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The circular object menu provides some shortcuts for adding messages, inspecting
			attributes, patching inlets and outlets, and locking objects that you may find useful 
			when patching.
	</bodytext>
	<a name="circular_locking"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Patching from the Object sectional menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over a Object segment of the circular menu, click to display the
			sectional menu's contents, and drag to select the <b>Lock</b> menu item.
			When you release your mouse, the your the object will display a green tinge and
			will be "locked" in place - you won't be able to move the object from its current
			position. This can be useful when patching in tight spaces or with a lot of objects.
		</li>
			<li>
			To unlock the object, click anywhere in the patcher window.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="circular_messages"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Patching from the Messages sectional menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over a Messages segment of the circular menu, click to display the
			sectional menu's contents, and drag to the message item you want to select.
			When you release your mouse, a  
			<link name="message" type="refpage">message box</link> 
			containing the message connected to the left inlet of the Max object will 
			automatically be created, ready for you to complete by typing in any arguments the 
			message may require.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_4.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="circular_attributes"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Patching from the Attributes sectional menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over a Attributes segment of the circular menu, click to display the
			sectional menu's contents, and drag to the attribute you want to select.
			When you release your mouse, an 
			<o>attrui</o> object containing the name of the attribute and connected to the left 
			inlet of the Max object will automatically be created.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_5.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="circular_prototypes"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Patching from the Prototypes sectional menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over a Prototypes segment of the circular menu, click to display the
			sectional menu's contents, and drag to the prototype you want to select.
			When you release your mouse, the user interface object you have selected will be
			replaced by the selected
			prototype for the object.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_6.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="circular_patching"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Patching from the Connect sectional menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on any Max object to select it and position your cursor on the left edge
			of the object or the object box to display the circular object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Move your mouse over a Connect segment of the circular menu, click to display a
			listing of all the inlets and outlets of the object and the type of data they expect.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_7.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Drag to select an object inlet or outlet.
			When you release your mouse, the your cursor will be automatically change into 
			the end point of a patch cord connected to the inlet or outlet you selected,
			ready to be connected to another Max object.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/circular_menu_8.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
</vignette>
