<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Color Picker">
	<header1>
		The Color Picker
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		The Color Picker lets you edit the colors of Max objects.
		You can choose from among several different schemes for 
		specifying colors. You can add transparency to the colors you specify by using an
		opacity slider located at the bottom of every Color Picker tab.
		<i>Opacity</i> 
		corresponds to the alpha channel value in ARGB or
		RGBA color specifications, with an alpha of 0 being completely 
		transparent and and alpha of 1 being completely opaque.
		When working with the Color Picker, you can save the colors 
		you create as individual swatches or as groups called 
		<i>palettes</i>
		, and specify colors in Max object 
		<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspectors</link>
		by dragging and dropping from the Color Picker.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<b>
			<i>Note: The standard Macintosh Color Picker does not support
		selecting colors using floating-point values in the range 0. - 1.0.
		However, the Macintosh Color Picker can be enhanced with third-party 
		plug-ins, so there are easily available solutions that will add this
		functionality to your Color Picker. If you are running a Windows 
		version of Max, this functionality is already available to you as
		one of the tabs.</i>
		</b>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<a href="http://ahtenindustries.com/FloatColorPicker/">Click here to download a floating-point RGB extension to the color picker.</a>
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Showing the Color Picker
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on a Max object to select it and choose 
			<b>Color...</b> 
			from the Object menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			In an 
			<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link> 
			window, click a color swatch to open the Color Picker.
		</li>
			<li>
			To hide the Color Picker, click the close button at the top of the 
			Color Picker window.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<header2>
		Specifying Colors
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		The top of the Color Picker includes a set of tabs that let you choose
		different ways of specifying colors. Click on a tab to choose the 
		method you want. Max will remember your choice and always show you
		the method you chose last.
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		The 
		<i>Color Wheel</i> 
		tab allows you to set color and opacity manually. 
		Click and drag in the color wheel to set the color. The vertical slider 
		on the right sets brightness. 
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/color_picker_tab1.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		The 
		<i>Color Sliders</i> 
		tab allows you to set color value numerically, 
		using various modes such as RGB (0-255), HSB and CMYK and grayscale.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/color_picker_tab2.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>	
		The 
		<i>Color Palettes</i> 
		tab allows you to 
		<link anchor="colorpalette" module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">create color palettes</link>
		you can save and recall as an aid to consistent design.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/color_picker_tab3.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		The 
		<i>Image Palettes</i> 
		tab is the image picker, which allows you to sample colors from an image. The default image, usefully, is a full spectrum.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/color_picker_tab4.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>	
		The 
		<i>Crayons</i> 
		tab is the crayon picker which allows you to select a color from a friendly box of crayons.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/color_picker_tab5.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		Each and every one of the Color Picker's tabs has a rectangle that
		shows the currently selected color located at the top of the picker,
		and an Opacity slider and swatch drawer located at the bottom.
	</bodytext>
	<header2>
		Working with Swatches
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		When you have specified a color you think you'll want to use again,
		you can create a 
		<i>swatch</i>
		. The Color Picker includes a swatch
		drawer which is always visible at the bottom of the Color Picker.
		The Swatch drawer can hold up to 256 different swatches. You can
		'open' the swatch drawer by clicking on the dot at the bottom of
		the window and pulling down.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/color_picker_swatch_enlarge.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		You can store your own swatches here as you work. Once stored, you
		can drag and drop these colors to apply them within the Color Picker
		itself, of drag and drop them to set colors in a Max object's 
		<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspectors</link>.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Saving a Swatch
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click in the color display are in the upper part of the
			Color Picker and drag down to a square in the swatch drawer.
			When you release the mouse, the color will be saved. If you
			click and drag onto a previously stored swatch, it will be
			overwritten and the new swatch color will be saved instead.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/color_picker_swatch_create.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Using a Swatch
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click in a swatch or the color display and drag it 
			to any swatch in a Max object's
			<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>
			or 
			<o>attrui</o> 
			object to set the color.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/color_picker_swatch_apply.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="colorpalette"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>	
		Creating A Color Palette
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the Color Palettes tab.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click the gear icon and choose 
			<b>New...</b> 
			to display a blank palette.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/color_picker_new_palette.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click the add button (
			<b>+</b>
			) to add the current color to the palette or 
			add colors by dragging from the upper Color viewer or by dragging swatches
			from the swatch panel. You can type in names to help you identify colors
			for future reference.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
