<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Changes in the Max Environment">
	<header1>
	Changes in the Max Environment
	</header1>
	<br /><space />
<a name="compatibilitypreferences" />
<header2>
		Preferences
	</header2>

		<bodytext>
			If you are a user of an older version of Max, your preferences will 
			not be imported. Preferences include the search path additions you 
			specified in the 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="file_preferences_window">File Preferences window</link>, 
			as well as <link type="vignette" module="core" name="audio_status">DSP settings</link> 
			and 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="midi_setup_window">MIDI port mappings</link>. 
			You will need to recreate these settings. Saving your 
			preferences will not overwrite those of older versions.
		</bodytext>
<a name="compatibilitysearchpaths" />
<header2>
		The Search Path
	</header2>

		<bodytext>
			A Mac-specific feature some users may have used in the past was the ability 
			to alias a folder within the search path. This is no longer supported 
			unless the alias is specifically added to the search path. For example, if 
			you have an aliased folder called MyWork, you cannot drag it into your 
			patches folder and have all its contents available in the search path - you'll
			need to add it manually.
		</bodytext>
	<br /><space />
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Adding an aliased folder to the search path
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Choose <b>File Preferences</b> from the Options menu to open the File Preferences window.
		</li>
		<li>
			Click the Choose button in an available slot.
		</li>
		<li>
			Use the file dialog that appears to navigate to your aliased folder and choose it.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br /><space />
	<header2>
		File Extensions
	</header2>

		<bodytext>
			Max uses file extensions to determine the 
			type of file you are trying to open. For example, when saving a Max patcher file, 
			you must use the <i>.maxpat</i> extension or your file will not open properly.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Some Macintosh users of previous versions of Max may have been somewhat casual about 
			file extensions, instead relying on the Macintosh OS's legacy "file type" mechanism to 
			identify their files. This is no longer advisable. Furthermore, when importing old 
			documents, Max pays more attention to the file extension that than it does to 
			any Macintosh OS "file type" information that might be associated with the file. For 
			example, if you have a text file and you have made the mistake of giving it 
			the extension <i>.mxb</i>, Max will think it is a Max binary file until you change 
			the extension. 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			This has always been the case on Windows; now it is the case on the Macintosh as well.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="compat_doc">More information about converting old patcher files</link>.
		</bodytext>
	

</vignette>
