<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Converting Older Max Documents">
	<header1>
	Converting Older Max Documents
	</header1>
		<bodytext>
			Previous versions of Max had two different document formats: binary and text. 
			This was originally a reflection of the need to save space; roughly, the binary 
			format was the text format with a cheap form of data compression applied to it. 
			In the current version of Max, there is a single format based on the JSON specification. 
			JSON is a way to specify data similar to XML, but far more readable since it 
			resembles Javascript source code. In addition, Max documents are encoded with 
			Unicode (UTF-8) and can be given long filenames.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			While both the old and new documents specify a patcher in terms of objects 
			and connections, the details of how this is accomplished in each format are 
			very different. In addition, far more data at higher resolutions is saved 
			in a Max document, so Max does not provide a way to "export" patches 
			you create to the older format. Max can, however, import patches, either 
			text or binary, from older versions of Max. Below we describe some of the 
			problems you may encounter when importing older documents.
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			Missing or Incompatible Objects
		</header2>		
		<bodytext>	
			If you have an old Max 4 folder and you just try to open one of your patches 
			in Max, you may encounter a lot of missing files or objects, because you haven't 
			set up your
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="file_preferences_window" anchor="searchpath">search path</link>
			so that Max can see the files needed by the patch. For more information on moving 
			older (Max 4 or previous versions) search path to Max, read
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="compat_oldandnew">Using Old and New Versions of Max on the Same Machine</link>.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>	
			In the event that an older third-party object will not work in Max, 
			you will see errors in the Max window saying the objects have failed to load, 
			but in rare cases, incompatible objects may crash Max. Cycling '74 is working 
			with developers of third-party objects to help implement any changes that need 
			to be made.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			 Text Encoding
		</header2>		
		<bodytext>	
			Documents created with version 4 of Max (and earlier) use legacy Mac-specific text 
			encodings (even on Windows) that needs 
			to be converted to Unicode. In some cases when using non-Roman characters, conversion 
			may not happen perfectly because the actual encoding in the document being imported 
			cannot be identified.
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			Object Sizes and Fonts
		</header2>		
		<bodytext>	
			Max uses anti-aliased fonts that may be difficult to read when displayed at 
			small sizes. You cannot switch off the anti-aliasing, but you have several 
			options for making text larger:
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
		<li>
			You can select all the objects you want to make larger, then open the 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="fonts">Fonts Window</link>
			by choosing <b>Show Fonts</b> from the Object menu. Use the font panel's 
			size control to increase the point size of the text objects.
		</li>
		<li>
			You can use the Scaling Bar to increase the size of the selected objects in a patch.
		</li>
		<li>
			You can zoom into the patch temporarily. Choose <b>Zoom</b> In from the 
			View menu, or choose <b>Navigate Zoom</b> to use the 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="patcher_window_navigation" anchor="navwindow">interactive zoom tool</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>

		<header2>
			Behavior of Specific Objects
		</header2>		
		<bodytext>	
			Some Max objects no longer support certain messages or features. For a complete list, review 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="compat_objects">Object-Specific Changes</link>.
		</bodytext>
	

</vignette>
