<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Old and New Versions of Max">
	<header1>
	Using Old and New Versions of Max on the Same Machine
	</header1>
		<bodytext>
			As you make the transition to Max from an older version, you 
			may wish to run old and new versions side-by-side or at least 
			keep them both installed at the same time. Here are some hints 
			to make this easier.
		</bodytext>	
	<header2>
		Don't Overlap Your Search Paths
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			By default, when you install Max, everything except your 
			preferences will go into a single self-contained folder. Nothing 
			from your previous Max version will interfere with the installation 
			of any previous version of Max.
		</bodytext>	
		<bodytext>
			For best results, you'll want to keep two separate copies of 
			every file specific to each version. The main reason to do this 
			is that Max 4 cannot read patcher files created by later versions of Max, so if 
			these files begin to appear in the search path, Max 4 may not 
			behave properly. Not only will it be unable to interpret the 
			files as patchers, it does not know how to read Unicode text files, 
			so it can't necessarily read them as text files either. If you 
			write data files containing extended characters with objects such 
			as <o>table</o> or <o>coll</o>, they may be unreadable in older versions. This 
			issue extends to things like scripts for the <o>js</o> and <o>jsui</o> objects. 
			If you use extended characters in these scripts, you cannot easily 
			maintain a single version that works in both Max 4 and later versions. The moment 
			you save the file in Max 6, it will be unreadable in Max 4. The 
			Javascript engine used by Max requires the script to be in Unicode. 
			Max can convert legacy Macroman text files to UTF-8, but it will 
			not save in this format.
		</bodytext>	
		<bodytext>
			Mac users might be tempted to use the technique of creating an alias 
			to their Max 4 world and dropping into their Max search path. As 
			explained 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="compat_environment" anchor="compatibilitysearchpaths">here</link>, 
			folder aliases do not work in the search path in Max as they did 
			in versions 4 and earlier. Furthermore, the same version compatibility and search 
			path problems will crop up if you do this.
		</bodytext>	
		<bodytext>
			Instead of trying to manage one set of files, make a copy of all 
			your files and move that into your Max search path.
		</bodytext>	
	<header2>
		Preferences Won't Overlap
	</header2>	
		<bodytext>
			As explained 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="compat_environment" anchor="compatibilitypreferences">here</link>,
			Max 6 does not share preferences with older versions. Preferences files from older 
			versions are not compatible. Do not attempt to copy 
			them. Use the Max environment to create new preferences.
		</bodytext>		
	<header2>
		CPU Utilization
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			With comparable 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="scheduler_preferences">scheduler settings</link>,
			Max has a slightly 
			higher CPU utilization doing nothing than earlier versions do. So if you 
			are trying to gain a bit more CPU while using Max, you may 
			wish to quit earlier versions temporarily.
		</bodytext>	
	<header2>
		Virtual MIDI Ports (Mac only)
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			One confusing issue that arises when trying to run Max at the same time as an 
			older version of Max is that the virtual MIDI ports created by the Mac version 
			called "to Max 1" and "from Max 1" appear to be doubled. Due to the fact 
			that old patches may store references to these virtual ports by name, it was not 
			possible to give them new names to distinguish them from the ports in 
			earlier versions. Furthermore, you will be confused because one of the ports with the same 
			name will do the opposite of what you expect (it will be output when you expect 
			it to be an input). To help eliminate the confusion, the virtual ports of other 
			applications are shown in italics in the Max MIDI Setup window.
		</bodytext>	
</vignette>
