<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Data Monitoring Objects">
<header1>
Data Monitoring Objects
</header1>
<body>
A number of Max objects can be used to observe what's going on in your patch. Connect these objects to a source of data to see what is going on.
</body>
<body>
Note: in many cases, rather than add additional objects to your patch, you can use <link type="vignette" module="core" name="watchpoints">watchpoints</link>, or the <link type="vignette" module="core" name="signal_probe">signal</link> or <link type="vignette" module="core" name="matrix_probe">matrix</link> probes to observe messages and data.
</body>
<header2>
Objects that Display Numbers and Messages
</header2>
<ul>
	<li>The <o>print</o> object posts anything it receives to the Max window. This is useful if you want to look at a sequence of numbers or messages and might miss something happening rapidly.</li>
	<li>The number box shows <link type="refpage" name="number">integer</link> or <link type="refpage" name="flonum">floating-point</link> numbers it receives.</li>
	<li>Connect a source of messages or data to the right inlet of the <link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> and the box will change to display what was received (no prepend set required).</li>
	<li>The <o>number~</o> object is the audio equivalent of the number box. Other MSP objects that display signals include <o>meter~</o>, <o>levelmeter~</o>, <o>scope~</o>, and <o>spectroscope~</o>.</li>
	<li>The <o>jit.cellblock</o> object can be used to show matrix data numerically.</li>
</ul>
<br />
<header2>
Objects that Capture Data
</header2>
<ul>
	<li>The <o>print</o> object can be used to capture data if you don't mind looking it in the Max window.</li>
	<li>The <o>capture</o> captures data in variety of formats for examination in a text window.</li>
	<li>The <o>capture~</o> is the equivalent of the capture object for audio signal data.</li>
	<li>With a little more work, the <o>text</o>, <o>table</o>, and <o>coll</o> objects can be used to store sets of data.</li>
</ul>
<br />
<header2>
Objects that Report Performance Information
</header2>
<ul>
	<li>To determine the amount of absolute time something takes, use the <o>cpuclock</o> object.</li>
	<li>To determine the amount of logical (scheduler) time something takes, use the <o>timer</o> object.</li>
	<li>To measure the frame rate of a Jitter patch, use the <o>jit.fpsgui</o> object.</li>
	<li>To measure audio CPU utilization, use the <link type="refpage" name="adstatus">adstatus cpu</link> object.</li>
</ul>
</vignette>
