<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Searching the Documentation">
	<header1>
	Searching the Documentation
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
	You can search the Max documentation by using the Max documentation window. 
	It allows you to perform searches and to explore documentation resources.
</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Using documentation search results
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>Choose <b>Max Help</b> from the Help menu to display the documentation window.
		</li>
			<li>Click in the Search field at upper right of the documentation window and enter the text you are looking for.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/search1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>The results of your search will be returned, organized by types. The results displayed will include Max Object refpages, Max Tutorials, and Vignettes.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/search2.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>Use the disclosure triangles to hide or display categories to refine your search.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/search3.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>Click any item link to display your choice in the documentation window.</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
		Once you enter some search text, you can also see the results for any matching filenames in the 
		<link module="core" name="file_browser" type="vignette">file browser</link>.
</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Exploring the Documentation
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
		The documentation window also allows you to explore the online documentation by type.
	</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Max Help</b> from the Help menu to display the documentation window. You'll see tabs for Max objects, tutorials and vignettes.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/search4.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>To explore the documentation, click on a tab.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/search5.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>Use the disclosure triangles to show you the documentation contents in greater detail.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/search6.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>Click any item link to display your choice in the documentation window.</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
</vignette>
