<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="File Browser Drag and Drop">
	<header1>
	File Browser Drag and Drop
	</header1>
<bodytext>
	Once you find files in the file browser, you can quickly incorporate them into patchers by dragging them. Files can be dragged <i>into patchers</i> as well as <i>onto objects</i>. Below are some common tasks you can accomplish with drag and drop.
</bodytext>
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Creating objects from the file browser
	</header2>
<ul>
	<li>
		Click on an object file in the file browser and
		drag into any empty space in an unlocked patcher window. You’ll see a translucent
		copy of the row from the file browser appear in the window when
		you drag the file into it.
	<br />
		When you release your mouse, a instance of the object will appear in the patcher.
	</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
	<br /><space/>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Creating read file messages for media files from the file browser
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on a media file an imagefile, an audiofile, or a moviefile in the File
		Browser browser display area and drag into any white space in an unlocked Patcher
		Window. You’ll see a translucent copy of the row from the File Browser appear in
		the unlocked patcher window when you drag your cursor into it.
		<br />
		When you release your mouse, a message box will appear in the Patcher Window that
		contains the Max message used to load the media file (e.g. <m>read</m><space/><bi>&lt;moviefile name&gt;</bi>,
		<m>open</m><space/><bi>&lt;audiofile name&gt;</bi>).
	</li>
	<li>
		You'll need to add a patch cord to connect newly created message box
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		Holding down the Option key (Macintosh) or Alt key (Windows) while dragging will
		show a pop-up menu. Although the contents of the menu will vary depending on what type of
		media file you choose, you are basically presented with the choice of creating a
		<link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> with the necessary message to load the file, or to instantiate a
		Max object that loads the media file.
	</bodytext>
</bluebox>
	<br /><space/>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Loading QuickTime movies from the file browser
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on a moviefile in the file browser and drag onto any <o>jit.qt.movie</o>
		object in a locked or unlocked patcher window. You’ll see a translucent copy of the row from
		the File Browser appear in the unlocked patcher window when you drag your cursor into it.
	<br />
		When you release your mouse, the QuickTIme movies will be read into the <o>jit.qt.movie</o>
		just as if you had used the <m>read</m> message.
	</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
	<br /><space/>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Loading audiofiles into MSP objects from the file browser
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on an audiofile in the file browser and drag onto any  <o>buffer~</o>, <o>waveform~</o>, or
		<o>sfplay~</o> object in a locked or unlocked Patcher Window. You’ll see a translucent copy
		of the row from the File Browser appear in the unlocked patcher window when you drag your
		cursor into it.
		<br />>
		When you release the mouse button, the audiofiles will be read into a <o>buffer~</o> object as if you had
		used the <m>replace</m> message or into an <o>sfplay~</o> object as if you had used the <m>open</m> message.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		Holding down the option key (Mac) or control key (Windows) while dragging will
		show a pop-up menu. You can choose to create a <link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> with the necessary
		message to load the file, or to instantiate a
		<o>buffer~</o> or <o>sfplay~</o> object that loads the media file.
	</bodytext>
</bluebox>
	<br /><space/>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Loading image files from the file browser
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on an image file in the file browser and drag onto any <o>fpic</o> or <o>jit.qt.movie</o>
		object in a locked or unlocked Patcher Window. You’ll see a translucent copy of the row from the File Browser
		appear in the unlocked patcher window when you drag your cursor into it.
		<br />
		When you release the mouse button, the image file will be read into a the <o>fpic</o> or <o>jit.qt.movie</o> object as if you had used the read message.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		Holding down the option key (Mac) or Alt key (Windows) while dragging will
		show a pop-up menu. You can choose to create a <link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> with the necessary
		message to load the file, create an <o>fpic</o> object that loads the media file, or
		create an embedded image.
	</bodytext>
</bluebox>
	<br /><space/>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Creating menus from the file browser
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on a folder in the file browser and drag into any white space in an unlocked Patcher
		Window. When you You’ll see a translucent copy of the row from the File Browser appear in
		the unlocked patcher window when you drag your cursor into it.
		When you release your mouse, a <o>umenu</o> object will appear that contains
		the names of all the files in the folder.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		Holding down the option key (Mac) or Alt key (Windows) while dragging will
		show a pop-up menu. You can choose to create a <link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> with the necessary
		message to load the file, create an <o>fpic</o> object that loads the media file, or
		create an embedded image.
	</bodytext>
</bluebox>
	<br /><space/>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Loading a patcher into a bpatcher from the file browser
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on the name of a patcher file in the file browser 
		area and drag onto any <o>bpatcher</o> object in an unlocked patcher window. 
		When you release the mouse button, the patcher file will be loaded into the <o>bpatcher</o> 
		object, or will replace any patcher file currently loaded.
	</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
</vignette>
