<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Error Messages">
	<header1>
	Errors and Error Messages
	</header1>
	<header2>
	Error Messages
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Max prints an error report in the Max window when you make a programming mistake.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(picture)
		</bodytext>
	<br />
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Tracing an error message
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Click on the error message you want to trace in the Max window. The
		error message will be highlighted.</li>
		<li>
			Click on the Show Object icon on the Max window toolbar. The Max object
		associated with the error message will appear, highlighted with a green tinge.</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			(picture)
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			If the object is contained in a subpatch, the subpatch will open in an
			unlocked Patcher window.
		</bodytext></bluebox>
	<br />
	<header2>
	Scheduler and Timer Errors
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			When you make an error while programming with Max that requires your immediate
			attention, the error is reported in a dialog box.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/error_messages1.png"  />
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			The most common of these errors is a Stack Overflow.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			It is possible to get Max working so hard it does not have time to respond
			to your commands (say, if you have a number of metro objects sending out bang
			messages as fast as they can, or if you have created a loop that overloads
			Max, causing a Stack Overflow error). When this happens, you may need to stop
			the Max scheduler, restart the scheduler, or both.
		</bodytext>
	<br />
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Stopping the Max scheduler
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Hold down the Command key (Macintosh) or the Control key (Windows) and type
			a period. The scheduler will be stopped
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			When Max's timer is stopped, you will see a message in a dialog box.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/error_messages2.png"  />
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br />
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Starting the Max scheduler
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Choose <b>Resume</b> from the Edit menu. The Max scheduler will restart.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br />
	<header2>
	Error Message Listings
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Below is a list of error messages you may encounter, along with likely causes
			of each message.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>"$" variable out of range></m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when you refer to an argument number out of the range $1 - $9 in a message
			sent to a <o>message</o> box.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: error opening file (and variations)</m>.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			An error occurred opening a file that was properly located. Most likely the
			file or media has a problem.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: </m><bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: can't open</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a patch is loading or when an object is created that reads its data from
			a separate file. The file that was to be read in automatically was not found in
			Max's search path or was not a type of file that the object is capable of opening. The
			erroneous filename has usually been specified as an argument to an object such as
			coll, seq or table. Make sure that the file is in Max's search path.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: bad argument</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when creating a new object with typed-in arguments. There is something
			wrong with what you typed after the name of an object. Usually the object is
			expecting a symbol, and you typed in a number, or vice versa. Check the object's
			argument specification list on the Reference page.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: bad arguments for message</m><space/><bi>&lt;message&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when an object receives a message that it understands, but one of the
			arguments in the message is not what the receiving object expected. Usually the
			object was expecting a symbol argument and got a number, or vice versa. Check
			the object's input list on the Reference page.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: doesn't understand</m><space/><bi>&lt;message selector&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when an object receives a message that it doesn't expect. It is possible
			to make patch cord connections that will result in improper messages being
			sent to an inlet. For example, Max will let you connect the outlet of a
			<o>message</o> box to almost any inlet, because there's no way of knowing what
			message will come out of the outlet. In such a case, the error does not
			become evident until you test the program and the message is actually sent.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: message too long</m><space/><bi>&lt;message&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			A message was sent that contained more elements than the object can
			handle.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: missing arguments for message <bi>&lt;message&gt;</bi><space/></m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when an object receives a message that it understands, but one or
			more of the expected arguments in the message is missing. Check the object's
			input description on the Reference page.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: No such object</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when creating a new object or loading a document. When you are editing a
			patcher, and you type the name of a nonexistent object into an object box (or
			the name of an object or subpatch that is not in Max's search path), Max
			produces this error message.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			When you open a document that contains an object that Max cannot find (either
			because it is not located in Max's search path or because it just doesn't exist),
			Max displays the object as if it existed, except that the object name is
			surrounded by a dotted outline in the object box, and an error message is
			printed in the Max window. This preserves the connections to the object box
			in case you can retype the object to create it properly.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(picture)
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			A similar box is created when a user interface object referenced inside a
			file cannot be located.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: fragment file not found</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			This error occurs when a collective references an external object that
			has been improperly stored in the collective. It should not happen with
			the current version of Max.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>:</m><space/><bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: file not found</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			This error occurs when a file name is either passed to an object as the
			argument to a <m>read</m> message or stored within an object saved within a
			patcher. The file cannot be located, either within Max's search path
			or with its full pathname.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;symbol&gt;</bi><m>: bad arg types</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a patch is running and a symbol is received in the inlet
			of a bitwise operator such as &amp;, |, &lt;, or &gt;. Make sure
			that only number messages are sent to bitwise operators.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;symbol</bi>&gt;<m>: no such object</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a message is sent to a <o>send</o> object, or to a message
			box that contains a semicolon followed by the name of a receiver,
			and there is no <o>receive</o> object with the name specified in the
			<o>send</o> object or <o>message</o> box.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;number&gt;</bi><m>: not a symbol</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when the element that follows a semicolon in a <link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link>
			(specifying a receiver for the message) is not a symbol.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: bad magic number</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: corrupt binary format file</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			The file you tried to open is corrupted or is not a properly
			formatted Max document. Restore the file from a backup copy if available.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: error creating file</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			There was an error writing a file; the disk may be write-protected or full
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: out of memory writing file</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			There is insufficient memory to write the file you're trying to
			save. If possible, close other files and windows that don't
			relate to the file you're saving.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad: Floating point exceptions were caught</m><space/><bi>&lt;number of exceptions&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) This message is sent to the max window when audio is stopped
			if floating point exceptions were caught while processing audio. The tells
			you how many exceptions were caught to give you an indication of the severity
			of the problem. This can be triggered by underflow of float-ing point
			operations causing denormal numbers to be generated. You may want to try
			modifying your patcher to cause the exceptions to stop as it may affect the performance.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_mme: unable to open wave input device. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_mme: unable to open wave output device. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_mme: unable to start output. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_mme: unable to start input. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_mme: stopping due to error. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_mme: No MME input or output devices found. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) Please check that you have the latest driver update for
			your audio device. Please exit all other audio applications, reboot if
			necessary, and try again. Also, please check your settings in the Audio
			Status window to insure appropriate choices are selected for Input Device,
			Output Device, Sampling Rate, IO Vector Size, and Signal Vector Size.
			If the problem persists, contact Cycling '74 support.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: can't create directsound object. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: can't create directsoundcapture object. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: Failed to set cooperative level to priority. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: Failed to create primary buffer. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: Failed to set format of primary buffer. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: failed to create output DirectSoundBuffer. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_ds: No directsound input or output devices found. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: unable to Play output buffer. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: unable to Start input buffer. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ad_directsound: stopping due to error. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) Please check that you have the latest driver
			update for your audio device. Please exit all other audio
			applications, reboot if necessary, and try again. Also,
			please check your settings in the Audio Status window to insure
			appropriate choices are selected for Input Device, Output Device,
			Sampling Rate, IO Vector Size, and Signal Vector Size. If the
			problem persists, contact Cycling '74 support.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>ASIOCreateBuffers error </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) A problem was encountered initializing the
			ASIO device. Please check that you have the latest driver
			update from your audio device manufacturer. Please also try
			different settings for the device buffer sizes and latency in
			the control panel for your audio device provided by your device
			manufacturer. Check that another audio application is not using
			the audio device. Also check that the audio device is not the default
			audio device for Windows System Sounds.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>bad message</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Same as <bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: doesn't understand</m><space/><bi>&lt;message selector&gt;</bi>.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>bad receiver</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Same as <bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: doesn't understand</m><space/><bi>&lt;message selector&gt;</bi>.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>bag | float | int | pack | table: missing or incorrect arguments to send</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when the patch is running and a <o>bag</o>, <o>float</o>, <o>int</o>, <o>pack</o>, or <o>table</o> object
			receives a <m>send</m> message without an argument, or with an argument that is not a
			symbol or is not the name of an existing <o>receive</o> object.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>can't connect</m><space/><bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><space/><m>to </m><bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Advisory message produced when you try to connect an outlet to an inlet that doesn't
			understand the message sent by the outlet. You will also notice that the inlet was
			not highlighted when you dragged the mouse over it.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>can't fragload</m><space/><bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: missing </m><bi>&lt;libraryname&gt;</bi><m>, err</m><space/><bi>&lt;number&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			An external object that depends upon a particular shared library was not loaded
			because the shared library is not available. You'll see this error if you try to
			use an object for MSP with the non-MSP version of Max (the missing library will
			be called MaxAudioLib in this case) or if you try to use some external objects
			created for an earlier version of Max. Otherwise, to solve this problem, you
			may need to relocate the shared library or update your system.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>check failed: t_newptr in overdrive</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			This message occurs when an object attempts to allocate too much memory at
			interrupt level. Unless it represents a bug in the object, it may mean that you'll
			have to modify your patch to use a <o>defer</o> object where memory is being allocated.
			One example would be attempting to store large lists of data in a <o>coll</o> object.
			See the <o>defer</o> Reference page for more details.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>check failed: <bi>&lt;message&gt;</bi><space/></m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when there is a bug in the Max application or in an external object.
			Please report the con tents and context of any such message to Cycling '74.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>could not load QuickTime function: </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) A necessary QuickTime function was not found. Make sure
			you have installed QuickTime for Windows and chosen a complete install
			of all optional components.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>Error loading external file</m><space/><bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when Max is installing an external object in the startup folder. The external
			object file is damaged. Try restoring a copy from the original disk.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>funbuff: bad file type</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>funbuff: file not found</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a patch is loaded or when a <o>funbuff</o> object is created that
			reads in from a separate file. There was an error in reading a file into
			a <o>funbuff</o> object, either because the file was not in the proper format (it must
			start with the word <m>funbuff</m>, followed by a space-separated list of numbers)
			or because a Max or text file with that name could not be found. Ensure
			that the file is in located in Max's search path, and that it is in the proper format.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>grab: can only connect to leftmost inlet</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when you try to connect the right outlet of a <o>grab</o> object to the wrong
			inlet of another object. The right outlet of the <o>grab</o> object should be connected only to
			the leftmost inlet of other objects.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>graphic: </m><space/><bi>&lt;name&gt;</bi><space/><m>already exists</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when you create a graphic object with a name that has already been
			taken by another object, such as a <o>table</o> or <o>send</o>/<o>receive</o> object pair.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>inlet: wrong message or type</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a patch is running and an object receives a message that it
			doesn't expect in some inlet other than the left inlet.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>midi_mme: unable to open midi input device </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>midi_mme: unable to open output device </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) Max was unable to open the MIDI input or output device.
			Please exit from all other MIDI applications and try again.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>MSP/ASIO: Unexpected error loading driver </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>MSP/ASIO: error loading ASIO driver for </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>MSP ASIO: Error loading driver </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) A problem was encountered loading the ASIO driver.
			Please check that you have the latest driver update from your audio
			device manufacturer. Check that another audio application is not
			using the audio device. Also check that the audio device is not the
			default audio device for Windows System Sounds.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>MSP ASIO: initialization error </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>MSP/ASIO: can't deal with bufsize</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>MSP/ASIO: data format</m><space/><bi>&lt;format&gt;</bi><space/><m>not supported</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>MSP/ASIO: driver start error </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) A problem was encountered initializing the ASIO device.
			Please check that you have the latest driver update from your audio
			device manufacturer. Please also try different settings for the device
			buffer sizes and latency in the control panel for your audio device
			provided by your device manufacturer. Check that another audio application
			is not using the audio device. Also check that the audio device is not the
			default audio device for Windows System Sounds.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>No help available for</m><space/><bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi>.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			A help file in the max-help folder cannot be located for the named object.
			Restore the help file from your original Max disks.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>no resource</m><space/><bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			This error occurs when you are testing a standalone application and the
			Search for Missing Files option has been turned off. The named object or
			file has not been included in the collective from which the standalone
			was created, and since the runtime Max is not going to look for the file,
			it declares it missing after it was not found inside the standalone as a resource.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>not enough memory to open</m><space/><bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: can't load, out of memory</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			The file is too large to be opened. Note that to open a patcher
			file you need more memory than would be required to actually use the file.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>object box has comma or semicolon: </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Indicates that you typed a comma or a semicolon character into an object
			box. If this error occurs when reading in a patch, it is likely that the
			file is damaged.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>offscreen buffer couldn't be allocated</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Insufficient memory available when working with objects in a graphic window
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>patcher: unknown script keyword</m><space/><bi>&lt;keyword&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			A keyword argument to the script message to sent to the <o>thispatcher</o> object
			is not recognized.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>patcher connect: inlet</m><space/><bi>&lt;number&gt;</bi><space/><m>out of range</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when editing the name or arguments of an object that has already
			been created in a patcher, and patch cords that used to be connected to
			the object can no longer be connected. Changing the contents of the object
			box may change an object's number of inlets or outlets, or Max may be unable
			to create the object at all if you type in the wrong thing.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>QT images not supported in 8-bit color mode</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) You are trying to load a QuickTime image but your display
			resolution is set to 8- bit color depth. Change your Display Settings to
			increase your Color Depth, preferably to 24 or 32 bits.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>read failed</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a file is read into an object. Max encountered an error
			reading a file and could not load in the data. Check to make sure that
			the file is in the proper format for the object reading it in.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>rescopy: failed to add</m><space/><bi>XXXX N</bi>, <m>error</m><space/><bi>N</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when installing an external object. This message (especially if you
			see a lot of them) may indicate a problem with the Max Temp file used to store
			resources for external objects. If you only see one or two of these errors, it
			may be a resource missing in the object or a conflict between two or more
			objects attempting to use the same ID number. If <bi>XXXX</bi> is STR#, this
			problem only affects the strings shown when getting assistance on an object
			and should not be considered a major problem.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>rescopy: failed to get</m><space/><bi>&lt;resource type&gt;</bi><space/><bi>&lt;ID number&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when installing an external object. The external object file is
			corrupted. Restore a new copy of the external object from your original disk.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>script: </m><space/><bi>&lt;keyword&gt;</bi><m>: variable</m><space/><bi>&lt;variablename&gt;</bi><space/><m>empty</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a script message to the <o>thispatcher</o> object references a
			variable that is no longer assigned to an object.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>script: </m><space/><bi>&lt;keyword&gt;</bi><m>: no variable</m><space/><bi>&lt;variablename&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a script message to the <o>thispatcher</o> object references a
			variable that has not yet been defined or given a value.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>script: instance</m><space/><bi>&lt;number&gt;</bi><space/><m>of</m><space/><bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><space/><m>not found</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when using the <m>nth</m> script message to the <o>thispatcher</o> object and the
			specified index is greater than the number of objects of the specified
			class in the patcher.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>script: name</m><space/><bi>&lt;variablename&gt;</bi><space/><m>already in use</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a script message to the <o>thispatcher</o> object attempts to assign an
			object to a variable name that is already been used. This error will not occur if
			you choose <b>Name...</b> from the Object menu to assign a name to an object.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>send: </m><space/><bi>&lt;symbol</bi>&gt;<m>: already exists</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>receive:</m><space/><bi>&lt;symbol</bi>&gt;<m>: already exists</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when you type in a name as an argument to a <o>send</o> or <o>receive</o> object
			which is already being used for a <o>table</o> object or some other object.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>sxformat: illegal type in message</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when the patch is running and some message other than an int is
			received in the inlet of an <o>sxformat</o> object.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>text:</m><space/><bi>&lt;filename&gt;</bi><m>: file is protected</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			You have tried to open a Max binary patcher file protected against editing as text
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>textbox: bad args</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when opening a Max document. The document has been damaged.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>Unable to load MaxQuickTime.dll. Error code. </m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			(Windows only) A required component of Max was missing. Try reinstalling to see if
			it fixes the problem. If not please contact Cycling '74 support and provide the
			message and that was reported.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>warning: extra arguments for message</m>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when an object is given more typed-in arguments than it expects, or
			when too many arguments are present in an incoming message. Usually this is
			just a warning of something that is not quite right but is basically harmless.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<m>warning:</m><space/><bi>&lt;objectname&gt;</bi><m>: no port</m><space/><bi>&lt;symbol</bi>&gt;, <m>using</m><space/><bi>&lt;default port&gt;</bi>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Occurs when a port argument is typed into the object box of a MIDI object,
			and the port name is not currently valid. The valid port names are listed
			in the MIDI Setup dialog box. The default port is the first name in the
			device list in the MIDI Setup dialog.
		</bodytext>
			
			
</vignette>
			
