<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="The Object Explorer Toolbar">
	<header1>
	The Object Explorer Toolbar
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		The toolbar located at the bottom of the Object Explorer lets you set the behavior of the Explorer.
		The first four buttons provide options to control the Object Explorer window itself, while the next 
		three are sensitive to what object is currently selected (If no object is selected, the icons are disabled).
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>Explorer Settings</i> button sets Object Explorer user preferences.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_buttons_1.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>View by Icon</i> and <i>View by Name</i> buttons
		toggle between two different views of objects in the Object Explorer.
		If you like to remember objects visually, you can view by icon. rather than name.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_buttons_2.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_buttons_3.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>Hide Object Details</i> button sets hide or show the Object Details portion of the Object Explorer.
		If object details are hidden, click on the <i>Show Object Details</i> button to display a short description 
		of the selected object and additional links to documentation. 
		If the Object Details panel is hidden, the Explorer will display a larger number of object categories.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_buttons_4.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>+</i> button will place a copy of the selected Max object at the center of your Patcher Window.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_buttons_5.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>?</i> button will display the Max help file for the selected object.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_buttons_6.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>Reference</i> button will open the Reference file for the selected object.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_buttons_7.png"/>
	</bodytext>
		<header2>
		Object Explorer Preferences
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		You can set preferences that control the conditions under which the
		Object Explorer appears and how it behaves to improve your personal
		patching experience.
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
	<li>
		The <i>Create Object Box Before Showing Explorer</i> option gives experienced Max users the benefit of quick 
		access to the Object Explorer without it 'getting the way'  On double-click, a new object is created and 
		you can continue typing the object name and text competition will assist you. Double-click or drag an object 
		from the Object Explorer to override the newobject creation.
	</li>
	<li>
		If <i>Hide Explorer After Creating Object</i> is enabled, the Object Explorer window will disappear after 
		object creation. The Object Explorer will remain visible when objects are dragged from it, regardless of 
		the state of this option. This option is disabled when the sidebar is open.
	</li>
	<li>
		The <i>Show Explorer Below Target</i> option positions the Object Explorer window right below where you 
		clicked so you don't have to mouse across your screen. This is particularly handy if you've set the 
		Object Explorer to hide after creating an object (Normally, Max remembers where you placed the Object Explorer).
	</li>
	<li>		
		The <i>Make Icons Larger</i> and <i>Make Icons Smaller</i> menu options scale the icon size. This option is 
		disabled if the Object Explorer is set to 'View by Name'
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Setting Object Explorer Preferences
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the Explorer Settings button in the Object Explorer toolbar to show the menu options and choose an 
			option from the menu you wish to set or disable. The enabled state of a menu item is shown by a check mark
			next to the item.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/explorer_toolbar_1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
</vignette>
