<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Setting Default Fonts">
	<header1>
	Setting Default Fonts
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
You can assign a <i>default font</i> and size used to make new objects in a patcher. There is a default font for newly created patchers set in the <link module="core" name="preferences_window" type="vignette">Preferences Window</link>, and a default font specific to a patcher set in the <link module="core" name="patcher_inspector" type="vignette">patcher inspector</link>, or by using the <link module="core" name="font_panel" type="vignette">font panel</link>.
</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Setting the default font new patchers
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Open the preferences window by choosing <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Mac) or Options menu (Windows).
	</li>
			<li>
		Click the Font tab.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click in the Value column for the Default Font setting. Use the <link module="core" name="font_menu" type="vignette">font menu</link> to choose the desired font.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click once in the Value column Default Font Size setting to use the font size menu to choose a new font size, or double-click to enter a font size by typing.
	</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Setting the default font for a single patcher
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Open the <link module="core" name="patcher_inspector" type="vignette">patcher inspector</link> by choosing <b>Patcher Inspector</b> from the View menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click the Font tab.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click in the Value column for the Default Font Name setting. Use the <link module="core" name="font_menu" type="vignette">font menu</link> to choose the desired font.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click once in the Value column Default Font Size setting to use the font size menu to choose a new font size, or double-click to enter a font size by typing.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
	Alternatively, the <link module="core" name="font_panel" type="vignette">font panel</link> will show the default font for a patcher when it is visible and the topmost window is an unlocked patcher window with no objects selected. If you change the default font and/or size when no objects are selected, the patcher's default font will change, and the next text object you create in the patcher will use the new font.
</bodytext>
</vignette>
