<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Information">
	<header1>
	Information
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			Max provides you with several ways to find out about the Max application itself,
			the function of the Max objects you use as you program, and the flow of data through a Max patch.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			As you navigate using your mouse, the Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>
			provides you with help about Max menus, the interface, objects in a Patcher window, and
			Max’s various Inspectors, Palettes, and Windows.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Assistance</link>
			gives you a brief description of the use of each inlet and outlet
			of a Max object in unlocked (or locked) Patcher windows.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><link module="core" name="quickref" type="vignette">The Quickref menu</link>
			provides you with a listing of all the messages that
			Max object understands, a simple message sending and querying facility, and
			access to Mac help files and Reference pages.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Each Max object has its own definitive online
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="help_docs" type="vignette">Reference page</link>
			and
			<link anchor="helpfile" module="core" name="help_docs" type="vignette">help file</link>
			that provides information about the function of the object and its use. You can consult view
			the Max reference and Help files directly from the Max application as you work.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			You can search for objects and media using the Max
			<link module="core" name="file_browser" type="vignette">File Browser</link>,
			and save the materials you have for future reference.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			You can monitor what is happening in your patch as you work by using
			<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">watchpoints</link> -
			a kind of “wiretap” for Max patch cords, and the
			<link module="core" name="signal_probe" type="vignette">signal probe</link>.
		</bodytext>
</vignette>
