<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Inspector">
	<header1>
		The Object Inspector
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>object Inspector</i> is used to edit the 
		<link module="core" name="attributes" type="vignette">attributes</link> 
		of Max objects. In addition to providing a complete listings of all
		attributes associated with a selected Max object, you can use the 
		Inspector to set attributes, perform various patching tasks, and to
		<link module="core" name="freezing_attributes" type="vignette">frozen attributes</link> 
		to save their initial state.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The
		<link module="core" name="inspector_toolbar" type="vignette">Object Inspector toolbar</link> 
		provides easy access to patching activities you'll use often.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>		
		In addition to the Inspector for Max objects, there is also another Inspector 
		available that lets you set the behavior of your current Patcher itself rather
		than individual objects in a patch- the
		<link module="core" name="patcher_inspector" type="vignette">Patcher Inspector</link>.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Showing the Object Inspector
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
		There are several ways to show the Inspector window for an object:
	</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Is the 
		<link module="core" name="sidebar" type="vignette">Sidebar</link>
		is not already visible, click on the Open Sidebar button in the 
		<link module="core" name="patcher_toolbar" type="vignette">Patcher window toolbar</link>
		and click on the Inspector tab in the Sidebar to show the object Inspector.
	</li>
			<li>
		Position the mouse on the left side of the object until the
		Circular object menu
		appears. Click in the <b>Object</b> segment of the wheel and choose 
		<b>Inspector</b> from the pop-up menu.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/inspector_opening1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select an object or multiple objects in your patcher window by Shift-clicking or clicking
		and dragging an outline around the objects and click the Inspector button in the 
		<link module="core" name="patcher_toolbar" type="vignette">Patcher window toolbar</link>.
		When one or more objects are selected, click the Inspector button in the 
		Patcher window toolbar. When you open the object inspector on multiple objects, 
		only the attributes <i>shared</i> by the objects are shown.
	</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bodytext>
		<link module="core" name="attributes_inspecting" type="vignette">For information about editing attributes using the object Inspector, click here.</link>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<link module="core" name="freezing_attributes" type="vignette">For information about freezing attributes, click here.</link>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<link module="core" name="dragging_attributes" type="vignette">For information about patching using the Inspector, click here.</link>
	</bodytext>
</vignette>
