<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Interface Settings">
	<header1>
	Setting Interface preferences
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Interface</i> category of the Max Preferences window
			lets you set a number of preferences that affect how
			you work with Max.
		</bodytext>
	<a name="allwindowsactive"/>
	<header2>
	All Windows Active (Windows systems only)
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			By default, only Max objects in the frontmost window can respond to 
			mouse clicks, and any other windows must be clicked on to bring them
			to the foreground. When the All Windows Active checkbox in the 
			Interface pane is checked, Max objects in background windows will 
			respond to the mouse, but you'll need to either click on the title
			bar or choose the window's name from the Max Window menu to bring it
			to the foreground.
			<br/>
			You can only type numbers into one of the Max number box objects if
			the window in which the number box is located is in the foreground.
			However, keystrokes on your computer keyboard will be sent out the
			outlets of any <o>key</o>, <o>keyup</o>, or <o>modifiers</o>
			object in any loaded patch or subpatch regardless of the All Windows
			Active setting.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="defaultimageresolution"/>
	<header2>
	Setting image resolution preferences
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			Several Max objects (<o>jit.qt.grab</o>, <o>jit.dx.grab</o>, <o>jit.qt.movie</o>) 
			allow you to save loaded image files or individual
			frames of a Jitter matrix. You can set a preference for the default 
			resolution for any image files you save.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Setting a default image resolution
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options 
			menu (Windows) to show the Preferences Window. Locate the <b>Interface</b>  
			category and click in the Values
			column for the Export Image Resolution setting and choose a resolution
			from the pop-up menu (the options are 72, 96, 150, or 300 DPI).
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<header2>
	Displaying floating-point numbers
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			The way floating-point numbers are stored on your computer means that not all 
			numbers can be represented. This means that you will often see values such as 2.3 
			displayed as 2.29999. Clicking in the Float Display Correction checkbox will
			make the Max application round numbers and truncates them at what it guesses 
			is the least significant digit.
		</bodytext>
	<header2>
	Setting file saving preferences
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			By default, the Max application will automatically save any previously 
			created patcher file in its original location without reminding you
			of what that location is. If you would like to be gently reminded of
			a file's current location every time you save it, click in the
			Save Dialog Shows File Location checkbox in the Interface category.
		</bodytext>
</vignette>
