<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Using and Editing Example Devices">
	<header1>
	Using and Editing Example Devices
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
	Max for Live includes several different types of example devices and Max patches 
	to demonstrate the kinds of higher-level devices that can be created using
	Max for Live, to help you learn to use Live, and provide you with tools to help 
	you create your own Live devices.
</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
<header2>
	Important Note
</header2>
<bodytext>
	Before editing an example device, 
	always 
	save a copy of the device 
	and work on the copy so as
	not to overwrite or otherwise mangle the original example.
</bodytext>
	<br/>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
<bodytext>
	One way to learn Max for Live is to start with someone else's work,
	analyze the Max patch to see how it works, and then to 
	begin by making changes to the patch to do new things. 
	In addition to the 
	Max Documentation 
	itself and the extensive set of 
	<link module="core" name="live_resources_tutorials" type="vignette">Max for Live tutorials</link>,
	there are several several tools and tips that will help
	you as you begin to investigate example Max patches
	created by others.
</bodytext>
	<ul>
	<li>
		The Max example patches contains UI objects that contain
		<link module="core" name="annotations" type="vignette">Max annotations</link>.
		When you position your cursor over a
		user interface object in a device's window, you'll see a description of
		what the control does in Live's Info View.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/example-devices1.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
	<li>
		The
		<link module="core" name="live_parameterswindow" type="vignette">Parameters Window</link>
		will show you all of the parameters in a Max for Live
		device when you're editing it. You can use the Parameters
		Window to display and also to edit the parameter settings.
	</li>
	<li>
		You can use the Max
		Patcher window's 
		<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>
		to find out about the Max objects that are in the patch,
		what those objects do.
	</li>
	<li>
		Some of the Max for Live example patches included in the 
		<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-essentials//">Max for Live Essentials</a>
		and
		<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-pluggo-live//">Max for Live Pluggo for Live</a>
		Live packs contain UI objects that include
		<link module="core" name="annotations" type="vignette">Max annotations</link>.
		When you position your cursor over a user interface object in a device's window, 
		you'll see a description of what the control does in Live's Info View.
	</li>
	<li>
		When a Max for Live device's patcher window is open,
		You can use the Max
		Patcher window's 
		<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>
		to find out about the Max objects that are in the patch,
		what those objects do.
	</li>
	</ul>
<bodytext>
		<img src="images/example-devices2.png"/>
</bodytext>
	<ul>
	<li>
		The
		<link module="core" name="live_parameterswindow" type="vignette">Parameters Window</link> 
	 	lets you view and edit all of the parameters in a device.
	</li>
	</ul>
</vignette>
