<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="The Parameters Window">
	<header1>
		The Parameters Window
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>Parameters Window</i> provides an 
		overview of all the <link module="core" name="live_parameters" type="vignette">parameters</link> currently associated with a Max 
		for Live device, whether they are built into the UI objects or 
		defined via <o>pattr</o> objects.
	</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Displaying the Parameters Window
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Choose <b>Parameters</b> from the View menu when a device patcher window is the frontmost window. The Parameters window will appear.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/parameters_window1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<ul>
		<li>
		The <b>#</b> column displays the setting for the <m>Order</m> attribute,
		which can be used to set the order in which parameters
		are recalled when a device is loaded. By default, all attributes are recalled
		sequentially/at one time. By setting an attribute to have a lower order number,
		you can recall parameter values in complex patches whose initial values may
		need to be calculated based on initial or preset values so that the dependencies
		are preserved.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>L</b> column displays the setting for the <m>Link to Scripting Name</m> attribute, which
		can be used to link the Scripting Name used with the <o>pattr</o> family of objects and
		patcher scripting to the <m>Long Name</m> and <m>Short Name</m> attributes. If the attribute
		names are linked, the box is checked and the name of the parameter is shown in a different 
		color text.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/parameters_window2.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		The <b>Name</b> column displays either the <m>Scripting Name</m> attribute or the 
		<m>Long Name</m> attribute, depending on whether or not they are linked.
		The <m>Long Name</m> attribute sets the name that appears in Live's automation view.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Short Name</b> column displays either the <m>Scripting Name</m> attribute or the 
		<m>Short Name</m> attribute, depending on whether or not they are linked.
		The <m>Short Name</m> attribute sets the name that appears as a part of the UI object's display.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Type</b> column displays the <m>Type</m> attribute used to set the type of data associated with
		the object. The choices are:
		<br/>
		<br/>
		Float: floating point number
		<br/>
		Int: integer in the range 0-255
		<br/>
		Enum: enumerated list (used for objects such as <o>multislider</o> and <o>umenu</o> objects)
		<br/>
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Range</b> column displays the <m>Range/Enum</m> attribute that sets 
		either a minimum/maximum or a list of possible values associated with the object's output.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Mod Mode</b> column displays the <m>Modulation Mode</m> attribute that sets the type of 
		parameter modulation applied to the parameter. 
		The modulation modes are described
		<link anchor="parametermodulation" module="core" name="live_parameters" type="vignette">here</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Mod range</b> column displays the <m>Modulation Range</m> attribute that sets the low 
		and high range values within which a parameter is modulated. Some
		modulation modes 
		use these parameter ranges for truncating modulation data.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>I</b> column displays the <m>Initial Enable</m> attribute checkbox that enables or 
		disables setting an initial value as a part of a UI object's state.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Initial Value</b> column displays the initial value of the parameter if the 
		<m>Initial Enable</m> attribute is checked.
	</li>
		<a name="unitstyles"/>
		<li>
		The <b>Unit Style</b> column displays the <m>Unit Style</m> attribute used when adding 
		labels to UI object displays. The unit style type for display can be set using the
		object's 
		<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link> .
		The choices are:
		<br/>
		<br/>
		Int: integer
		<br/>
		Float: floating point
		<br/>
		Time: output values will have a ms (milliseconds) label. Larger values automatically display seconds and milliseconds.
		<br/>
		Hertz: output values are labeled in Hz (Hertz). Larger values automatically display in kHz.
		<br/>
		deciBel: output values are labeled in dB
		<br/>
		%: output values are displayed as an integer percentage value
		<br/>
		Pan: output values are labeled as Left/Right pan integer values based on the range set for the object.
		When a range value between negative and positive integer values (e.g. -100. 100.), negative values will
		be labeled as left or right channel settings (-100L, 100R).
		If the range settings are have an upper range value of 0, the value will be reported as <m><i>value</i>L</m>.
		only Left channel values will be displayed.
		If the range settings are have an lower range value of 0, the value will be reported as <m><i>value</i>R</m>.
		<br/>
		Semitones: displays values as negative/positive integer semitones for tuning displays
		<br/>
		MIDI: displays integer values in the range 0 - 127 as MIDI note numbers (e.g. C#-2).
		<br/>
		Custom: the label is user-definable, and is settable
		<link anchor="customunitstyles" module="core" name="live_parameters" type="vignette">using the UI object's Inspector</link> .
		<br/>
		Native: displays the native unit style
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Exponent</b> column displays the exponential value used when calculating the object's output.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Steps</b> column displays the the precision of the object's output when clicking and dragging. (The computer's keyboard can be used to enter any value.)
	</li>
		<li>
		The <b>Value</b> column displays the current value.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Locating a Parameter Object
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Click on the blue info icon in the left column for the parameter you
		want to locate and choose <b>Reveal in Patcher</b> from the
		pop-up menu. The object associated with the parameter will be highlighted.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/parameters_window3.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Setting Parameter Object Values
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Double-click in the Value column for a parameter setting to show a 
		cursor and text box. Type in a new value or symbol for the initialization 
		value, followed by a carriage return.
		<br/>
		You can also adjust the user interface object manually, 
		click on the blue info icon in the left column for the 
		parameter you want to set a value for and choose
		<b>Update Initial Value</b>.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click on the blue info icon in the left column for the parameter you
		want to set a value for and choose <b>Set to Initial Value</b> from the
		pop-up menu. The UI object will change to reflect the new initial
		value.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/parameters_window4.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Choose <b>Save</b> from the File menu to save the new initialization settings.
	</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
