<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Creating Max for Live Devices">
	<header1>
	Creating Devices
	</header1>
<bodytext>
	When you use Max for Live to create new devices, you always begin
	from a basic <i>template</i> - a Max device that contains 
	the necessary Max objects for receiving and transmitting audio or 
	MIDI data to and from other devices in the Devices area of a Live track. 
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	When you edit a Max device, you launch the Max application, but you can continue to listen to your device in Live as you edit it thanks to a feature known as <i>preview mode</i>. <link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_preview">More information about preview mode</link>.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	When your Max for Live device is complete, you can save it (along
	with any presets you may wish to create) in a central library that
	allows you to load your patch or preset from the Live File browser
	at any time in the future. 
</bodytext>
<br />
<bluebox>
<header2>
	Creating a New Device
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on the Devices button in Live's File browser to display
		the list of available devices. 
	</li>
	<bodytext>
	<img src="images/creating-devices1.png" />
	</bodytext>
	<li>
		Click on the arrow to the left
		of the folder marked Instruments, MIDI Effects, or Audio Effects
		to show the available devices and their presets.
	</li>
	<bodytext>
	<img src="images/creating-devices2.png" />
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		Each of these folders contains a Max template "starter"
		device you can use when creating Max for Live devices.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		A device called Max Instrument is listed in the Instruments folder. It
		can be inserted on a Live Audio track or on a Live Instrument	
		track to process audio from a synth device.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		A device called Max Instrument is listed in the Instruments folder.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		A device called Max MIDI Effect is listed in the MIDI Effects folder.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		These devices can only be inserted on Instrument tracks. 
	</bodytext>
	<li>
		Click on a Max for live device in Live's File Browser and drag it 
		to the Devices Window for a Live Track. 
	</li>
	<bodytext>
	<img src="images/creating-devices3.png" />
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		A device window that contains a simple Max patch will appear. 
		Each patch contains the necessary Max objects and the connections 
		necessary to pass audio and/or MIDI between any audio or MIDI 
		devices you have inserted before or after the Max device.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
	<img src="images/creating-devices4.png" />
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		Note: Max for Live files have their own file format (.amxd) which 
		cannot be edited outside of Max for Live. You can drag an .amxd 
		file using your computer's Finder into the Live Devices area to 
		load the file, and you can also drag an .amxd file from your 
		mailbox to load it.
	</bodytext>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
<header2>
	Saving a New Device
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		To save a device, click on the close button in the patcher's title bar
		or choose <b>Save</b> from the Max File menu. If you are saving a newly
		created device, a file dialog will appear and ask where you want to save the file.
	</li>
	<bodytext>
		If you do not explicitly specify a location to save your device, it will
		be saved in a default location inside Live's device library, where it will
		be available from Live's Browser.
	</bodytext>	
	<li>
		To see the current library of available devices, click on the arrow to the
		left of any of the three Max for Live device folders (the <m>Max Audio Effects</m>
		folder in the Audio Effects folder, the <m>Max MIDI Effects</m>
		folder in the MIDI Effects folder, or the <m>Max Instruments</m> folder in the 
		Instruments folder. The folder will open and any saved devices will be 
		displayed.
	</li>
	<bodytext>
		<b>Note</b>: You can save a Max for Live device to any other location
		you wish, but it will not be displayed or available to Live's File Browser.
	</bodytext>	
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<header1>
	Copying Examples
</header1>
<bodytext>
	Max for Live contains a number of helpful
	<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_resources">examples and tutorials</link>
	that you can use as starting points for your own investigations
	or creations. Any time you open one of these devices and decide 
	to modify its contents, <m>you should save your work as a copy</m> of
	the existing patches that come with Max for Live to avoid problems
	associated with overwriting the original devices.
</bodytext>
<br />
<bluebox>
<header2>
	Copying a Device
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		To save a copy of a Max for Live device you want to edit, 
		choose <b>Save As...</b> from the File menu. A file dialog will 
		appear so you can give your device a new name.
	</li>
	<bodytext>
		If you do not explicitly specify a location to save your device, 
		your copy will be saved in a default location inside Live's device 
		library, where it will be listed in Live's file browser.
	</bodytext>	
	<li>
		When you save the device, the copy in Live will update automatically.
	</li>
<!-- commented out for now
	<bodytext>
	<img src="images/creating-devices8.png" />
	</bodytext>
-->
	<bodytext>
		Note: You can save a device to any location
		you wish, but it will not be displayed in Live's file browser. We recommend that you save Max devices <i>inside</i> the Live library.
	</bodytext>	
	</ul>
</bluebox>
</vignette>
