<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="MIDI Effect Building Blocks">
	<header1>
		MIDI Effect Building Blocks
	</header1>
<bodytext>
	The 
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-building-tools/">Max for Live Building Tools</a>
	Live Pack contains a set of fully
	functional Audio and MIDI effect devices that provide examples of various 
	kinds of operations and processes. You can use these patches 
	in series in your Live Session, or edit and recombine them to 
	make your own devices. 
</bodytext>	
<bodytext>
	Live Suite owners can download this Live Pack by choosing <b>Your Account > Your Packs</b>
	when logged in to the Ableton website and clicking on the download button to the Live Pack.
	To install the Live Pack, double-click on the <i>.alp</i> file
</bodytext>
<bluebox>
<header2>
	Finding the MIDI Effect Building Blocks
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		After you have installed the Live Pack,
		click on the Packs button in Live's File browser to display
		the list of currently installed Live Packs. In the column to the
		right, click on the arrow to the left of the M4L Building Tools
		folder to show the Live Pack contents.
	</li>
	</ul>
<!-- There is currently no pack to install, and so I can't get a screenshot. Commented out.
	<li>
		Click on the arrow to the left
		of the folder marked <b>Presets</b>.
	</li>
	<li>
		Click on the arrow to the left
		of the folder marked <b>MIDI Effects</b> to show the folder's contents.
	</li>
	<li>
		Click on the arrow to the left
		of the folder marked <b>Max MIDI Effect</b> to show the folder's contents.
	</li>
	<li>
		Click on the arrow to the left
		of the folder marked <b>Tools</b> to show the folder's contents.
	</li>
	<li>
		Click on the arrow to the left
		of the folder marked <b>Building Blocks</b> to show 
		Building Blocks.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
	<img src="images/midibuildingblocks1.png" />
	</bodytext>
-->
</bluebox>
<br />
	<header2>
	Overview of the MIDI Effect Building Blocks
	</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		<b>Max ANotePlayer </b>: a utility that functions as a keyboard
	</li>
	<li>
		<b>Max Humanizer </b>: Each incoming MIDI note is delayed a random amount of time.
	</li>
	<li>
		<b>Max NoteScalar </b>: Some examples of different ways to fill a table object in order to scale incoming MIDI notes
	</li>
	<li>
		<b>Max PitchScalar </b>: The behavior of this device imitates the behavior of Live's Scale MIDI effect
	</li>
	<li>
		<b>Max SimpleEcho </b>: Repeat a MIDI note with decreasing velocities
	</li>
	</ul>
	</vignette>
