<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Creating Audio Effect Devices">
	<header1>
	Creating Audio Effect Devices
	</header1>
<bodytext>
	Max for Live lets you create audio effects devices which receive audio
	input from the Live application process it in some manner, and pass 
	its audio output either back to the Live application, or to other
	downstream audio effects devices in the same audio track where the 
	device resides.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	By convention, a Max for Live device gets all its audio from the Live application
	using the <o>plugin~</o> object and sends its audio output using the 
	<o>plugout~</o> object. Audio input and output is limited to two channels.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	<b>Note:</b> Sending audio to another Max for Live 
	Audio Effect, Instrument, or MIDI Effect device using the Max 
	<o>send</o>, <o>receive</o>, <o>send~</o>, or <o>receive~</o>, objects is not supported.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	While creating a Max for Live audio device
	can begin by using the 
	Max for Live device templates, 
	you can use some of the Max for Live Audio devices, MIDI effects,
	and Instruments that come with Max for Live as your
	starting point.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	These resources include the following:
</bodytext>
<ul>
<li>
		The 
		<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_resources_exampledevices">Max for Live example devices</link> -
		are a set of Live devices that will provide 
		hours of enjoyment and serve as examples of high-level Max programming. The collection includes 
		one of each type of Live device - an audio effect, a MIDI instrument, and a MIDI effect.
	</li>
	<li>
		The 
		<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_audioexamples">Audio Effect Tools</link> demonstrate different tasks and aspects of device
		creation.
	</li>
	<li>
		The 
		<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_resources_tutorials">Max for Live Video Tutorials</link>
		contain examples of how to build Audio effects, MIDI effects, and Instruments.
	</li>
	<li>
		The  
		<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_audiobuildingblocks">Building Block devices</link> -
		are simpler example devices that can be used as-is or incorporated into your own devices.
	</li>
	<li>
		A subset of the original 
		<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_resources_pluggo">Pluggo</link> plug-ins
		from Cycling '74 have been recreated as Live devices.
	</li>
	<li>
		Additional 
		<link type="vignette" module="core" name="abstractions">abstractions</link> - 
		raw materials for the creation of Max for Live 
		Audio effects, Instruments, and MIDI effects are
		available as
		<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_resources_abstractions">Max for Live abstractions</link>
		These abstractions may be 
		of use to you if you are interested in using Max for 
		Live to control some portion of the Live application
		using the 
		Live API.
	</li>
	</ul>
<header2>
	Defining Latency for a Max for Live audio device
</header2>
<bodytext>
	When Live sends audio or when MIDI triggers audio through an effect created 
	using Max for Live, the events should all be time-aligned (e.g., if a MIDI 
	note falls on the downbeat, the MIDI Instrument's audio should also end up 
	in the mix on the downbeat). A device can provide latency information 
	to the Live host application so that the host can use <i>latency compensation</i> to adjust the relative timing of different audio tracks.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	When you use Max for Live, there are situations where it is useful to set 
	latency to counteract timing differences introduced in your signal processing. 
	If your signal processing patch requires you perform some kind of analysis 
	on a block of samples before any output is produced, you can enable latency 
	to make sure that the output from your effect will be correctly aligned 
	in the mix (whereas if you are creating a device in which signal delay is what 
	you intend, there's no problem and you don't need to set any latency).
</bodytext>
<br />
<bluebox>
<header2>
Setting Device Latency
</header2>
        <ul>
        <li>
        	With a device window as the topmost window, choose 
        	<b>Patcher Inspector</b>
        	from the View menu to show the <link type="vignette" module="core" name="patcher_inspector">Patcher Inspector</link>
        </li>
        <li>
			Double-click in the Value
			column for the Defined Latency attribute to show a cursor and text box.
			Type in a value for the latency value in <i>samples</i>, followed
			by a carriage return.
        </li>
        </ul>
</bluebox>
</vignette>
