<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Max For Live Example Devices">
<header1>
	Max For Live Essentials
</header1>
<bodytext>
	The 
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-essentials//">Max for Live Essentials</a>
	Live Pack contains a collection of audio effects, MIDI effects, drum synthesizers and control devices for Live 9.
	The collection includes:
</bodytext>
<ul>
<li>
	<b>Buffer Shuffler</b>: an update of a Max for Live devices originally released with Max for Live 1.0.
	It is an audio effect that reads incoming audio on Live audio track into a buffer and divides the buffer into 
	a user-definable number of slices. You can change the order in which steps are played back, the direction of 
	playback, and reorder playback on the fly using the user interface.
</li>
<li>
	<b>Convolution Reverb Suite</b>: A Max for Live device that offers high-quality convolution using Impulses taken from real 
	spaces or analog/digital hardware. Drop an impulse (or a single channel of a true stereo impulse stored as two 
	stereo files ending with L and R) to load it in the convolution engine. Offline control is offered over the 
	decay time and size of the virtual space. The predelay time, width of the reverb, and levels can be controlled 
	in real time. The <b>Convolution Reverb Pro</b> is similar to the Convolution Reverb, but adds more advanced features such as 
	realtime EQ, virtual positioning, modulation, frequency-dependent damping, and shape controls. The <b>IR Measurement Device</b>
	lets you load your own Impulse responses
</li>
<li>
	<b>Mono Sequencer</b>: An analog-inspired step sequencer with independent phases for parameters such as pitch, 
	octave, velocity, repeat and gate.
</li>
<li>
	<b>DrumSynth</b>: a collection of 13 Max for Live instruments that use synthesis to produce a wide variety of electronic drum 
	and percussion sounds. Each instrument is designed to replicate a particular type of drum sound, and they can be mixed 
	and matched in Live's Drum Racks to create custom synthetic drum kits. DrumSynth also comes with a number of pre-made 
	Drum Racks in a variety of styles.
</li>
<li>
	MIDI Effects and Control Devices: A collection of devices that include an LFO, and an Envelope Follower that function to 
	modulate control parameters in a Live Set.
</li>
</ul>
<bodytext>
	Live Suite owners can download this Live Pack by choosing <b>Your Account > Your Packs</b>
	when logged in to the Ableton website and clicking on the download button to the Live Pack.
	To install the Live Pack, double-click on the <i>.alp</i> file
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	In addition, you can also download copies of the original "Big Three" devices originally released with Max For Live 1.0
	as individual Live packs. You may find them to be useful programming examples, in addition to being a lot of fun.
</bodytext>
<ul>
<li>
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-buffer-shuffler/">The Max for Live 1.0 Buffer Shuffler</a>
</li>
<li>
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-loop-shifter/">The Max for Live 1.0 Loop Shifter</a>
</li>
<li>
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-step-sequencer/">The Max for Live 1.0 Step Sequencer</a>
</li>
</ul>
</vignette>
