<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Using pattr in Live Devices">
	<header1>
	Using pattr in Live Devices
</header1>
	<bodytext>
	Live-specific user interface objects such as <o>live.dial</o> save their state 
	within Live documents and presets. If you want to use standard Max objects 
	and have them interact with Live, you will have to make use 
	of the parameter mode features of <o>pattr</o> objects. The first step to 
	enable <i>parameter mode</i> in a <o>pattr</o> object. 
</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
Enabling Parameter Mode
</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select a <o>pattr</o> object and click the Inspector button in the Patcher toolbar 
		to show the object's
		<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click the Parameter tab at the top of the inspector window to show the Parameter attributes.
	</li>
			<li>
		Check the Parameter Mode Enable checkbox. 
	</li>
			<bodytext>
		Once you've enabled Parameter Mode, you can use the other
		<link module="core" name="live_parameters" type="vignette">parameter</link> 
		settings.
	</bodytext>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	The autopattr object does not work with Max for Live's parameter system
</header2>
		<bodytext>
	The <o>autopattr</o> object provides an easy to way manage the state of standard Max 
	objects, but it will not work with the parameter system, so objects that are attached 
	to an <o>autopattr</o> will not be seen by Live.
	If you want a pattr parameter to appear for modulation etc, you will need to add a <o>pattr</o>
	object for each instance.
</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Differences between Max and Max for Live usage of pattr and pattrstorage objects
</header2>
		<bodytext>
	Although the <link module="max" name="pattrchapter01" type="tutorial">pattr objects</link> can be used in the context of Max for Live, there are some differences as compared to normal Max use. Please read the appropriate section in the document <link anchor="pattr" module="core" name="live_limitations" type="vignette">Limitations of Max for Live</link> for more information.
</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
