<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Max for Live Instruments">
	<header1>
	Instruments
	</header1>
<bodytext>
	Max for Live lets you create Instruments which receive MIDI information
	from the Live application and use that information to generate audio
	output which can be sent back to the Live application or be further processed 
	by any number of Audio effects devices.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	The 
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-essentials//">Max for Live Essentials</a>
	Live Pack contains a collection of audio effects, MIDI effects, drum synthesizers and control devices for Live 9
	you can try, study, and modify.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	Live Suite owners can download this Live Pack by choosing <b>Your Account > Your Packs</b>
	when logged in to the Ableton website and clicking on the download button to the Live Pack.
	To install the Live Pack, double-click on the <i>.alp</i> file
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	The Max for Live Essentials pack contains the following example instruments:
</bodytext>
<ul>
<li>
	<b>DrumSynth</b>: a collection of 13 Max for Live instruments that use synthesis to produce a wide variety of electronic drum 
	and percussion sounds. Each instrument is designed to replicate a particular type of drum sound, and they can be mixed 
	and matched in Live's Drum Racks to create custom synthetic drum kits. DrumSynth also comes with a number of pre-made 
	Drum Racks in a variety of styles.
</li>
<li>
	<b>Mono Sequencer</b>: An analog-inspired step sequencer with independent phases for parameters such as pitch, 
	octave, velocity, repeat and gate.
</li>
</ul>
<!-- These are not here now, and they're not available as a Live Pack. Commented out
<li>
	The Max for Live tutorials are Live sessions
	that consist of a sequence of fully-featured devices
	to introduce you to the basics of programming
	and techniques for processing data. These tutorials include a sequence on
	<link type="vignette" module="core" name="live_resources_tutorials" anchor="instrument_tutorials">building FM synthesizers</link> .
</li>
-->
<bodytext>
	In addition, the
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-pluggo-live//">Max for Live Pluggo for Live</a>
	Live Pack is a collection of Max for Live devices derived from Cycling '74's Pluggo
	plug-in collection.	Several instruments are included there.
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	You can also download copies of instruments from the original "Big Three" devices originally released with Max For Live 1.0
	as individual Live packs. You may find them to be useful programming examples, in addition to being a lot of fun.
</bodytext>
<ul>
<li>
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-loop-shifter/">The Max for Live 1.0 Loops Shifter</a>
</li>
<li>
	<a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/packs/max-live-step-sequencer/">The Max for Live 1.0 Step Sequencer</a>
</li>
</ul>
<bodytext>
	The Max programming environment itself provides you with
	some helpful tools for one of the classic challenges of synth creation - the
	management of polyphony. The Max <o>poly~</o> object is created specifically
	to efficiently manage polyphony in the context of synthesizer design. The
	MSP tutorials also include a section on
	<link type="tutorial" module="msp" name="mspchapter21">using the poly~ object</link> .
</bodytext>
<bodytext>
	You can use any MIDI input object to receive MIDI data from Live application. You'll use the <o>plugout~</o> object for audio output.
</bodytext>
</vignette>
