<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="User Interfaces in Max for Live">
	<header1>
	User Interfaces in Max for Live
	</header1>
<header2>
	Device Width and Height
</header2>
<bodytext>
	By default, the <i>width</i> of a device created in Max for Live is
	based on the contents of your device patcher. It will be slightly wider than
	the visible objects in your device. Alternatively, you can explicitly define the width of your device
	to any size. If you change your mind, you can always reset the device
	width to the default behavior. The <i>height</i> of all Live devices is fixed at 169 pixels.
</bodytext>
<br />
<bluebox>
<header2>
	Defining a Fixed Device Width
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		While your Max for Live device patcher window is 
		open for editing, resize the window to be desired width you would like to see in Live.
		</li>
		<li>Choose <b>Set Device Width</b> from the View Menu.
	</li>
	<li>
		If desired, you now can resize the patcher window to a size convenient for editing. You will see a vertical line indicating the fixed width of the device. The width will update in Live the next time you save the device.
	</li>	
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
<header2>
	Using a Dynamic Device Width
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		While your Max for Live device patcher window is 
		open for editing, choose <b>Clear Device Width</b> from the View Menu. The next time you save the device, the width in Live will be determined by the contents of your patcher.
	</li>	
	</ul>
</bluebox>
	<br />
	<header2>
		Using Presentation Mode
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		Once you have your Max device up and running, you may
		want to present the user with only the user interface objects. Given the relatively small height of the
		Live Device view, it may
		be desirable to think of your interface separately from the logical position of
		the user interface objects in your patcher.
	</bodytext>
<br />
<bluebox>		
<header2>
	Creating a Presentation
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		In the unlocked Patcher window for your Max for Live device patch. select the user
		interface objects you want to be visible in the Device Window by shift-clicking to
		select them.
	</li>
	<li>
		Choose <b>Add to Presentation</b> from the Max for Live Object menu to add
		the objects to the Presentation layer.
		A pink border will appear around the object(s) you have selected.
	</li>
	<bodytext>
	</bodytext>	
	<bodytext>
		<b>Note:</b> All the user interface objects you want to add must be in the
		<i>top</i> level of your patch. If you include a <o>bpatcher</o> object
		containing part of a subpatch, that subpatch must also have its contents
		set to open in Presentation Mode (see below).
	</bodytext>	
	<li>
		Click the Presentation Mode button in the patcher toolbar to enter Presentation
		mode. When you switch to Presentation Mode, only objects you have added to the 
		Presentation layer will be shown and the word <b>(presentation)</b> will appear
		in the title bar of the patcher window. 
	</li>
	<bodytext>
	</bodytext>	
	<bodytext>
		You can also remove objects in the presentation by selecting them and 
		choosing <b>Remove from Presentation</b> from the Object menu. If you 
		are in Presentation Mode when you do this, the objects will disappear, 
		but they have not been deleted from the patch, just from the Presentation
		layer.
	</bodytext>	
	<li>
		While in Presentation Mode, you can reposition and change the color of
		user interface object, and also use resizing handles to change the size
		of some user interface objects (if an object can be resized, it will had
		resizing handles.
	</li>
	<bodytext>
	</bodytext>	
	<bodytext>
		You can use the Presentation Mode button to toggle between Patching
		and Presentation modes of a patch. If an object has been moved or
		resized in the Presentation layer, you will see it move and resize
		itself as you toggle the Presentation Mode.
	</bodytext>
	<li>
		When you are satisfied with the layout of your user interface, 
		choose <b>Patcher Inspector</b> from the Max for Live View menu.
	</li>
	<li>
		Check the <m>Open in Presentation</m> attribute.
	</li>	
	<bodytext>
		When you save and close your device patch, you will see your 
		user interface, and your Max for Live device patch will open
		in its edit window with the Presentation Mode enabled from now
		on. If you want to edit your patch, click the Presentation Mode 
		button to return to Patching Mode.
	</bodytext>
	</ul>
</bluebox>

</vignette>
