<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="64-bit Issues and Limitations">
	<header1>
	64-bit Issues and Limitations in Max 6.1
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The 64-bit implementation of Max is an exciting development for people creating 
			patches with large memory requirements, but it comes with some limitations. These 
			limits are based on underlying technologies that have either changed or are no 
			longer available. We are actively working to resolve these issues, and future 
			updates will improve the functionality of the 64-bit versions.
	</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<header2>
			QuickTime
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			The primary change is Max’s use of QuickTime as a media layer for graphic and audio 
			content: QuickTime is unavailable under 64-bit Windows, and has reduced functionality 
			in 64-bit MacOS. Therefore, objects and functions that were based on QuickTime 
			capabilities have to be rewritten to use other technologies. In the short term, 
			this means that the following objects are not supported in our 64-bit versions:
			<ul>
				<li>jit.avc</li>
				<li>jit.broadcast</li>
				<li>jit.desktop</li>
				<li>jit.displays</li>
				<li>jit.gl.text2d</li>
				<li>jit.lcd</li>
				<li>jit.qt.broadcast</li>
				<li>jit.qt.effect</li>
				<li>jit.videoout</li>
				<li>jit.vcr</li>
				<li>jit.qt.record</li>
				<li>spigot~	</li>
			</ul>
			In some cases, QuickTime was used was for media format conversion. As a result, only 
			JPG and PNG files can be used under 64-bit Windows for any Max object that includes 
			external graphics (such as pictctrl, pictslider and matrixctrl). Any PICT, GIF or 
			other file types must be converted to JPG or PNG formats to maintain cross-platform 
			compatibility.<br/>
			This media conversion issue also affects file reads into the buffer~ object. All 
			versions support reading/importing WAVE, AIFF and FLAC files. MacOS (32- and 64-bit) 
			can read formats supported by Apple’s Audio Toolbox system (which includes MP3, AAC, 
			SD2 and other file types). 32-bit Windows can support QuickTime movie-based audio 
			(including MP3). But for maximum cross-platform compatibility, WAVE, AIFF and FLAC 
			are the recommended formats.<br/>
			Finally, the following objects will have limited functionality due to changes in the 
			media layer:
			<ul>
				<li>jit.qt.movie</li>
				<li>jit.grab</li>
				<li>jit.qt.grab</li>
			</ul>
	</bodytext>
	<header2>
		Other Limitations
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			64-bit Windows no longer supports the “Microsoft Synthesizer” as a MIDI destination. 
			The “Microsoft GS Wavetable Synth” should be used in its place.
	</bodytext>
	<header2>
		Using the 64-bit Version
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			Windows 32- and 64-bit versions of Max are contained in separate installers. Externals 
			for these versions have different extensions: .mxe for 32-bit and .mxe64 for 64-bit.<br/>
			The MacOS installer is provided as a FAT bundle, and contains both 32- and 64-bit 
			versions. When installed, the application defaults to 32-bit mode. To change this, 
			select the application in the Finder and choose the “Get Info” menu option, then turn 
			off the “Open in 32-bit mode” setting in the General tab.<br/>
			Externals under MacOS are also FAT bundles, and contain both 32- and 64-bit versions 
			of the underlying code.<br/>
			3rd party external use is limited to the 32-bit version until the externals are converted 
			into 64-bit equivalents by the developer. 32-bit externals cannot be used by the 64-bit 
			version of the Max application.<br/>
	</bodytext>
</vignette>
