<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Max Window">
	<header1>
	Max Window
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The Max window displays status information, error messages, and warnings.
			You can get helpful advice about programming errors you make while you’re
			patching (putting an object into your patch that does not exist or misspelling
			the name of an object, for example) or while a patch is running (sending a
			message to a Max object that the object doesn’t understand or sending a message
			to an incorrect inlet) by looking at the Max window.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Showing the Max window
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Max Window</b> from the  Window menu.   To close the
			Max Window, click on the window's close button.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/max_window1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			The Max application keeps track of whether or not the
			Max Window
			is visible when you quit the program, and will hide or show
			the window when you relaunch Max based on its state when you
			last used Max.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<header2>
	About the Max window:
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			The Max Window toolbar includes several buttons used for common tasks.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Clear All</i> button clears all messages currently displayed in the Max window.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/max_window2.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Order By Time</i> button lets you see messages to the Max application in the
			time order they were received.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/max_window3.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Inspector</i> button lets you open the Inspector for any Max object
			that has a message listed in the Max Window..
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/max_window4.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Show Object</i> button is used to locate the object associated
			with a message in the Max Window.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/max_window5.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Rows of the Max window are color coded:
		</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
			status information or things you put there with the print object are in gray / white
		</li>
		<li>warnings are in yellow
		</li>
		<li>error messages are red
		</li>
		<li>internal errors (bugs in Max itself) are in blue
		</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
			Columns of the Max window are divided into <i>Object</i> and <i>Message</i>:
		</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
			The <i>Object</i> column displays the Max object associated with any error messages
			that are generated—either while you’re patching or while a patch is running.
		</li>
		<li>
			The <i>Message</i> column displays the
			<link module="core" name="error_messages" type="vignette">error messages</link>.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
			Click on the column heading to sort by object or message.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Click on the clock
			in the toolbar to sort by the order the message was posted. This is the default
			order and the one you’ll want to use most often.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Finding the Object that generated an Error Message
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			If a row of the Max window displays the name of an object, double-click
			on the row. The window containing the object that generated the error will be
			brought to the front, and a green tinge will appear over the object.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/max_window6.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Opening the inspector an object that generated a message
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			If a row of the Max window displays the name of an object, click on the
			row to select it. Click on the Inspector button in the Max Window toolbar
			to open the Inspector for the object.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Seeing the complete text of a message in the Max window
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			If the Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link> 
			isn't already visible, click on the Show Status Bar icon on the 
			Patcher window toolbar to show it. Move the mouse over a row of the Max window. 
			The entire contents of the row is displayed in the clue window.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
		You can find a complete listing of Max, MSP, and Jitter error messages
		<link module="core" name="error_messages" type="vignette">here</link>.
	</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Clearing the text in the Max window
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the <i>Clear All</i> button in the Max Window toolbar.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
