<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Max Menu Commands">
	<header1>
		Max Menus
	</header1>
	<header2>
		The File Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>New Patcher</b>
		will Create a new patcher window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>New From Template</b>
		will display a menu of current 
		Template
		files. When you choose a template, a new patcher using the chosen template file is created.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>New From Clipboard</b>
		will paste the contents of the clipboard into a new patcher window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>New Project</b>
		will display a file dialog box and let you name a new
		Project
		file. When you enter the project name, a new Project will be created
		and the Project window will appear.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>New File Browser</b>
		will display a new
		<link module="core" name="file_browser" type="vignette">File Browser</link>
		window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>New Text</b>
		will Create a new text editor window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Open...</b>
		will open an existing patcher, text file, or collective file.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Open as Text...</b>
		will open the source for a patcher in a text window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Open Recent Patcher</b>
		will display a menu of recently opened files and let you choose one.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Open Recent Project</b>
		will display a menu of recently opened 
		Project files and let you choose one.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Close...</b>
		will close the current window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Modify Read Only</b>
		will Permit a patcher loaded as an abstraction to be edited. If disabled, the current patcher window was not loaded as an abstraction.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Save...</b>
		will save the current window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Save As...</b>
		will save the current window with a new name.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Save As Project...</b>
		will save the current window as a self-contained file or an application.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Build Collective/Application</b>
		will save the current window as a self-contained file or an application.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Export Image...</b>
		will display a dialog box and save the currently selected objects in your patcher window as a visual image in .png format.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>List Externals and Subpatcher Files</b>
		will list of all the patcher files and external objects used by the current 
		patcher in the Max window.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
		The Edit Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Undo</b>
		will Undo the previous editing operation.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Redo</b>
		will Redo the previous editing operation.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Cut</b>
		will delete the selection and copy it to the clipboard.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Copy</b>
		will copy the selection to the clipboard.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Copy Compressed</b>
		will copy the selection to the clipboard in compressed text format.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Paste</b>
		will paste the contents of the clipboard into the current window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Delete</b>
		will delete the selection.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Duplicate</b>
		will duplicate the selection.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Select All</b>
		will select everything in the current window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Paste Picture</b>
		will create a .png object in the patcher with the image currently on the clipboard.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Paste Replace</b>
		will replace the currently selected objects with the object on the clipboard.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Encapsulate</b>
		will transform the currently selected objects into a subpatcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>De-Encapsulate</b>
		will transform the currently selected subpatcher into objects in the current patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Find...</b>
		will show the Find bar in the current window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Find Next</b>
		will select the next item that matches the current Find criteria.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Find Previous</b>
		will select the previous item that matches the current Find criteria.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Resume</b>
		will restart the scheduler when it has been stopped. This item is only enabled after a stack overflow has occurred.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
		The View Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>New View</b>
		will open another view of a patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Edit</b>
		will unlock the patcher window. If this is disabled, it means this patcher cannot be edited.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Presentation</b>
		will Switch between presentation and patching modes. Presentation mode is an easier way to create a user interface for your patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Patcher Inspector</b>
		will open an inspector window to edit settings that apply to an entire patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Parameters</b>
		will show the Parameters window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Dependencies</b>
		will show the Dependencies Window for the current patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Zoom in</b>
		will magnify the topmost patcher window by about 10 percent.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Zoom out</b>
		will zoom out the topmost patcher window by about 10 percent.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Show at 100%</b>
		will restore the zoom level of the topmost patcher window to 100%. 
		If this item is disabled, it means the window is currently shown at 100%.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Navigate Zoom</b>
		will open a small window in the corner of a patcher allowing you to change 
		the visible area of the patcher by dragging or changing the size of the 
		blue outlined box.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Grid</b>
		will show or hide the patcher's grid lines when the patcher is unlocked.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Sidebar</b>
		will show or hide patcher 
		<link module="core" name="sidebar" type="vignette">Sidebar</link>
		which contains the 
		<link module="core" name="max_window" type="vignette">Max window</link>, 
		<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>, 
		Reference, 
		and 
		<link module="core" name="object_explorer" type="vignette">Object Explorer</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Status Bar</b>
		will show or hide the 
		<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Toolbar</b>
		will show or hide the patcher 
		<link module="core" name="patcher_toolbar" type="vignette">Toolbar</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Show Connections</b>
		will Make patch cords visible when the patcher is unlocked.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Hide Foreground</b>
		will hide the foreground layer of objects in the patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Hide Background</b>
		will hide the background layer of objects in the patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Show CPU Usage</b>
		will show the CPU usage for signal processing in the patcher, 
		green (low) to red (high).
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Initial Window Location</b>
		will move the patcher to its initial window location.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Define Fixed Initial Window Location</b>
		will set the patcher's initial window location.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Clear Initial Window Location</b>
		will clear the patcher's initial window location.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	The Object Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Show Object Explorer</b>
		will open the 
		<link module="core" name="object_explorer" type="vignette">Object Explorer</link>,
		allowing you to choose a new object that will be created in the center 
		of the patcher window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Fix Width</b>
		will match the width of a text object to the width of its current text. 
		For non-text objects, Fix Width will return the object to its default size.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Name...</b>
		will edit an object's name for use with pattr objects or patcher scripting.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Inspector</b>
		will open the inspector window for the selected objects, where you can edit its
		<link module="core" name="attributes" type="vignette">attributes</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Show Fonts</b>
		will show the 
		<link module="core" name="font_panel" type="vignette">font panel</link>
		to change font settings on the selected object or topmost window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Color...</b>
		will open the 
		<link module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">Color Picker</link> 
		used for changing the basic color of the selected objects or patch cords.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Set to Default Values</b>
		will set object colors to default values.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Hide on Lock</b>
		will make the selected objects disappear when the patcher is locked.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Show on Lock</b>
		will make the selected objects visible when the patcher is locked.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Ignore Click</b>
		will set the selected objects to ignore mouse clicks.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Respond to Click</b>
		will set the selected objects to respond to mouse clicks.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Add to Presentation</b>
		will Add the selected objects to the 
		<link module="core" name="presentation_mode" type="vignette">presentation layer</link>, 
		where their size and position can be changed independently.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Remove from Presentation</b>
		will remove the selected objects from the 
		<link module="core" name="presentation_mode" type="vignette">presentation layer</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Send Message</b>
		will open a dialog where you can type in a message to send to the 
		selected objects.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Save Prototype</b>
		will save the selected object's settings so you can create a copy 
		from the 
		<link module="core" name="circular_object_menu" type="vignette">the circular object menu</link>
		or by applying to another object using the Prototype menu.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Prototype</b>
		will display a menu of 
		<link module="core" name="prototypes" type="vignette">prototypes</link>
		you can apply to the selected object.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
		The Arrange Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Auto Align</b>
		will align multiple objects to the left/topmost object's top or left edges.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Align</b>
		will display a menu that lets you choose alignment options - left, 
		center, right, top, middle, or bottom.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Distribute</b>
		will display a menu that lets you choose horizontal or vertical 
		object distribution.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Scale Spacing...</b>
		will place a sizing box around the selected objects permitting 
		you to resize them as a group.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Scale...</b>
		will place a sizing box around the selected objects permitting 
		you to adjust the spacing between them.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Snap to Objects</b>
		will constrain the movement of objects so they fall onto near 
		object's patcher placement.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Snap to Grid</b>
		will constrain the movement of objects so they fall onto grid lines.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Route Patch Cords</b>
		will route the placement of patch cords so that they avoid other objects.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Align Connections</b>
		will align objects to snap to the inlet/outlet it is connected to.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Remove All Segments</b>
		will remove all segments from a segmented patch cord.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Bring to Front</b>
		will move the selected objects ahead of all other objects. If this 
		command is disabled, it means the selected objects are already at the front.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Bring Forward</b>
		will move the selected objects' front-to-back ordering one step 
		toward the front. If objects are selected and this is disabled, 
		it means the objects are already at the front.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Send to Back</b>
		will move the selected objects behind all other objects. If this 
		command is disabled, it means the selected objects are already at the back.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Send Backward</b>
		will move the selected objects' front-to-back order one step toward 
		the back. If objects are selected and this is disabled, it means the 
		objects are already in the back.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Include in Background</b>
		will move the selected objects from the foreground (default) layer 
		to the background layer.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Remove from Background</b>
		will move the selected objects from the background layer to the 
		foreground layer.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
		The Options Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Overdrive</b>
		will enable or disable 
		<link anchor="overdrive" module="core" name="scheduler_settings" type="vignette">Overdrive</link>.
		Overdrive is a scheduler mode that runs timing objects 
		in a high-priority thread, resulting in more accuracy and less 
		interference from other 
		computer tasks.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Auto Fix Width</b>
		will automatically change the width of text object boxes as you type.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Segmented Patch Cords</b>
		will enable or disable drawing segmented patch cords.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Assistance</b>
		will enable or disable object 
		<link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">assistance</link>.
		When enabled, bubbles appear to describe objects' inlets and outlets when you move 
		the cursor over them. When disabled, the descriptions appear in the 
		Status Bar.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Help in Locked Patchers</b>
		will enable or disable the ability to open an object's help file by 
		option-clicking in a locked patcher window.
		When disabled, this only happens in an unlocked patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>MIDI Setup...</b>
		will display the
		<link module="core" name="midi_setup_window" type="vignette">MIDI Setup Window</link>
		where you can assign MIDI input and output ports to channel ranges 
		and letter abbreviations.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Audio Status...</b>
		will open the 
		<link module="core" name="audio_status" type="vignette">Audio Status window</link>
		where you can change audio driver and performance settings. 
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>OpenGL Status...</b>
		will open the 
		OpenGL Status window 
		to see properties of the graphics card on your computer.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Object Defaults...</b>
		will configure the default colors of patcher objects.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>File Preferences...</b>
		will open the 
		<link module="core" name="file_preferences_window" type="vignette">File Preferences window</link>, 
		where you can add folders to the Max search path.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
		The Debug Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Enable Debugging</b>
		will enable/disable debugging.
		When debugging is enabled, execution of a patch will stop at any active breakpoints. 
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Debugger</b>
		will open the Debug window, which shows the current program state when stopped at 
		<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">a Break Watchpoint</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Watchpoints</b>
		will open the 
		Watchpoints window 
		listing all currently active 
		<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">Break and Monitor Watchpoints</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Probing</b>
		will enable/disable 
		signal probing. 
		When probing is enabled, Max displays signal or matrix data from the 
		patch cord under the cursor in a locked patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Matrix Probe</b>
		will show the 
		<link module="core" name="matrix_probe" type="vignette">Matrix Probe window</link> 
		that displays current matrix data 
		transmitted through the patch cord under the cursor in a locked patcher.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Step</b> when program execution is stopped will send the next 
		pending message out an outlet and then suspend execution again.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Pause</b>
		will stop patch execution and shows where execution is suspended in the 
		<link module="core" name="tracing_tools" type="vignette">Debug Window</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Continue</b>
		will resume normal execution if program execution is stopped. Execution may stop 
		again if another 
		<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">Break Watchpoint</link> 
		is encountered.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Abort</b>
		will cancel any further execution when program execution is stopped.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Auto Step</b>
		will begin executing when program execution is stopped by triggering the next pending 
		message every two seconds, permitting you to watch your patch in slow motion.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Add Watchpoint - Monitor</b>
		will add a monitor watchpoint to the selected patch cord to record messages 
		passing through it that you can observe in the 
		Watchpoints window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Add Watchpoint - Break</b>
		will add a 
		<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">Break Watchpoint</link>
		(which will suspend execution when debugging is enabled) to the selected patch cord.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Disable Watchpoint</b>
		will disable the selected watchpoint.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Remove Watchpoint</b>
		will remove the watchpoint from the selected patch cord.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Remove All Watchpoints</b>
		will remove all watchpoints from all patchers.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Enable Patch Cord</b>
		will enable the currently selected patch cord(s).
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Disable Patch Cord</b>
		will disable the currently selected patch cord(s).
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
		The Window Menu
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Minimize</b>
		will reduce the window to the bottom of the screen.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Zoom</b>
		will toggle between full-screen and a window's normal size.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Send Window to Back</b>
		will move the window behind all other open windows.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Hide Subwindows</b>
		Close any open subpatcher windows of the topmost patcher window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Bring All to Front</b>
		Move all windows in front of the windows of other applications.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Max Window</b>
		will show the 
		<link module="core" name="max_window" type="vignette">Max window</link>. 
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Magnifier</b>
		will show the
		Magnifier window.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Clue Window</b>
		show the floating 
		<link module="core" name="clue_window" type="vignette">Clue window</link>. 
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		The remainder of the Window menu provides a listing of all currently 
		open patcher windows. Choosing a patcher from the menu will bring that
		patcher's window to Front.
	</bodytext>
	<header2>
		The Extras Menu
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		The Extras menu contains the names of patches that you can use for reference 
		or utility purposes. You can add your own patches to this folder
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing <b>Adding Extras...</b>
		brings up a panel with instructions about how to add patches to this folder.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		The remainder of the Extras menu provides a listing of all currently 
		available patchers. Choosing a patcher from the menu will open the patch.
	</bodytext>
</vignette>
