<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Controlling Jitter with Messages">
	<header1>
	Controlling Jitter with Messages
	</header1>
		<bodytext>
			As is the case with Max, you can control Jitter using the <link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> 
			object. Normally, the <link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> contains an 
			object, and you click on it or replace a variable typed into the 
			<link type="refpage" name="message">message box</link> to send a message down a patch cord to another
			Max object. However, if the message in a message box begins with a semicolon (;)
			followed by the word jitter, any message which follows will be sent directly
			to the Max application itself, just as though there were a <o>receive</o> object named "jitter".
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Another way this may be accomplished is to send messages via the <o>forward</o> object. 
			The forward object works similar to the send object, but is not restricted to sending to 
			named instances of the <o>receive</o> object. 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			These messages may be also included in a file named "jitter-config.txt", located anywhere 
			in the search path and they will be executed when Jitter loads. This is particularly 
			useful for the <m>nosplash</m> or <m>javaload</m> messages.
		</bodytext>
	<br /><space />
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			Sending a message to Jitter
		</header2>
			<ul>
			<li>
			Add a <o>message</o> box to your Patcher, and type in a semicolon and the
			word jitter (<m>; jitter</m>), 
			followed by the message you want to send. Your message box can 
			contain variables (e.g. <m>: jitter menubar $1</m>).
			</li>
			</ul>
		<bodytext>
			When you click on the <o>message</o> box or send it a <m>bang</m> or a value, 
			the message will be sent to the Max application.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br /><space />
		<bodytext>
			Here is listing of the messages you can send using this technique:
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			about
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
		Launches the Jitter about box.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			cursor
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Macintosh only) The word <m>cursor</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles 
			cursor visibility on/off.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			glattribpush
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>glattribpush</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles 
			safety measure used to isolate individual OpenGL objects from adversely affecting one 
			another's OpenGL state machine. By default, this is off (as of Jitter 1.5 and later), 
			but it may be useful to turn on if experiencing problems which seem like OpenGL state 
			from one object is affecting another object.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			glerrorcheck
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>glerrorcheck</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles 
			opengl error testing/reporting on/off. By default this is on, but turning it off 
			can give minor performance boost.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			html_ref
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>html_ref</m>, followed by a symbol that specifies the name of a Jitter object,
			launches the reference file for the object. (must be in Max's search path).
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			javaload
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>javaload</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles Jitter Java support on/off.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			launch_browser
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>launch_browser</m>, followed by a URL as a symbol, Launches the specified URL 
			in the default system web browser.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			menubar
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Macintosh only) The word <m>menubar</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles 
			menubar visibility on/off. Similar to Max's <m>showmenubar</m>, and <m>hidemenubar</m> messages. 
			When using in conjunction with the <o>jit.window</o> object's fullscreen attribute, it 
			is recommended that the <o>jit.window</o> object's <i>fsmenubar</i> attribute is used instead of 
			Jitter's <m>menubar</m> message, in order to prevent possible "pixel trash".
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			nosplash
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>nosplash</m>, followed by a one, disables the Jitter splash screen. 
			Only useful if contained in a jitter-config.txt file.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			parallel
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>parallel</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles parallel processor support. 
			The default is on if machine has multiple processors (or cores), and otherwise off.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			parallelthreads
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>parallelthreads</m>, followed by an integer, specifies the number of 
			threads used for parallel processor support. Default is the number of processors (or cores).
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			parallelthresh
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>parallelthresh</m>, followed by an integer, specifies matrix cellcount 
			above which parallel processors are used. Default is 10000 cells.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			pollthrottle
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>pollthrottle</m>, followed by an integer,  sets the number of 
			scheduler events to process per scheduler tick. Equivalent to Max's 
			<m>setpollthrottle</m> message.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			postversion
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
		Posts the Jitter version string in Max Window.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			queuethrottle
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>queuethrottle</m>, followed by an integer, sets the number 
			of low priority queue events to process per low priority queue service. 
			Equivalent to Max's <m>setqueuethrottle</m> message.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			spigot_cache
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Set the cache location. Cached audio will be saved:<br />
			0 = next to the original movie<br />
			1 = in the user-domain common folder (default)<br />
			2 = in the system-domain common folder<br />
			3 = in the user's temporary items folder<br />
			(symbol) = in the folder specified by the symbol<br />
			<br />
			<br />
			On Macintosh, the user-domain common folder is "~/Library/Application Support/Cycling '74/spigot-cache/". 
			<br />
			On Windows, this folder is
			"C:\Documents and Settings\(username)\Local Settings\Application Data\Cycling '74\spigot-cache\"
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			On Macintosh and Windows, the system-domain common folder is "(Cycling '74 support folder)/spigot-cache/".
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			The temporary items folder is typically invisible and inaccessible to normal users on both systems. 
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			spigot_cachesize
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Set the maximum size of the audio cache in megabytes. A cache size 
			less than 0 indicates that the cache should have no maximum size (the default).
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			spigot_getcache
		</header2>	
		<bodytext>
			Gets the cache location. The cache location is sent to any receive object with the same name as 
			the <sig>receiver</sig> argument, and is reported as a fully-qualified path.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			spigot_getcachesize
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Gets the cache site. The cache size is sent to any receive object with the same name as 
			the <sig>receiver</sig> argument.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			spigot_locatecache
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Opens the cache location in your Operating System's file browser.
		</bodytext>		
		<header2>
			spigot_purgecache
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Deletes the contents of the cache, to the limit specified by <m>spigot_cachesize</m>. 
			This method is called automatically every time jit.qt.movie opens a cached audio file, 
			or every time the cache size is set with the <m>spigot_cachesize</m> method.
		</bodytext>	
</vignette>
