<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Controlling Max with Messages">
			<header1>
			Controlling Max with Messages
			</header1>
		<bodytext>
			You can control Max, MSP, and Jitter using the <o>message</o> box object. Normally, 
			the <o>message</o> box contains an object, and you click on it or replace a variable 
			typed into the <o>message</o> box to send a message down a patch cord to another 
			Max object. However, if the message in a message box begins with a semicolon (;) 
			followed by the word max, any message which follows will be sent directly 
			to the Max application itself, just as though there were a <o>receive</o> object named "max".
		</bodytext>			
	<br /><space />
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			Sending a message to the Max application
		</header2>
			<ul>
			<li>
			Add a <o>message</o> box to your Patcher, and type in a semicolon and the
			word max (<m>; max</m>), followed by
			the message you want to send to Max. Your message box can 
			contain variables (e.g. <m>; max pupdate $1 $2</m>).
			</li>
			</ul>
		<bodytext>
			When you click on the <o>message</o> box or send it a <m>bang</m> or a value, 
			the message will be sent to the Max application.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br /><space />
		<bodytext>
			Here is listing of the messages you can send to the Max application using this technique:
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>buildcollective</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>buildcollective</m>, followed by a reference name symbol and an output filename, 
			builds a collective using the patcher associated with the symbol. The collective is named 
			with the output filename.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>checkpreempt</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>checkpreempt</m>, followed by a symbol, sends the current Overdrive mode to the 
			<o>receive</o> object named by the symbol.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>clean</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Causes Max not to show a Save Changes dialog when you close a window or quit, even if there are 
			windows that have been modified. This is useful in conjunction with the quit message below.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>closefile</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>closefile</m>, followed by a symbol, closes the patcher file previously opened with the 
			<m>openfile</m> message to Max associated with the symbol.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>db.exportmetadata</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Causes Max to write the metadata information currently stored in the database 
            to a file. An optional argument can be used to specify a filename.
            If no filename is specified, the metadata is backed up to a file in your preferences folder.
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>db.importmetadata</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Causes Max to load metadata information from a previously stored file into 
            the Max database. An optional argument can be used to specify a filename - when 
            no argument is specified, Max will look for a backup file 
			from a previous call to db.exportmeta in your preferences folder. 
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>db.reset</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Causes Max to recreate the database Max uses when operating (e.g. the 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="file_browser">File Browser</link>).
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>debug</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>debug</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles the sending of Max's internal debugging 
			output to the Max window. Debug information may be of limited use for anyone who isn't debugging Max itself.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>enablepathcache</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>enablepathcache</m>, followed by a zero or one, turns on (or off) Max's search path cache. 
			This should only be done if you noticed unusual behavior when opening files.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>enablerefresh</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Macintosh only) The word <m>enablerefresh</m>, followed by a zero or one, toggles an alternative 
			to the standard way in which the screen contents are updated, resulting in better visual performance. 
			This feature is enabled by default. The rate at which refresh is done can be set by using the 
			<m>setrefreshrate</m> message.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>externs</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			List all of the external objects currently loaded in the Max window.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>fileformat</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>fileformat</m>, followed by two symbols that specify a file extension and a 
			four-character file type, tells Max to associate a filename extension with a particular 
			filetype. The message <m>max fileformat .tx TEXT</m> associates the extension <i>.tx</i> with TEXT 
			(text) files. This allows a user to send a message read george and locate a file with 
			the name <i>george.tx</i>. It also ensures that files with 
			the extension <i>.tx</i> will appear in a standard open file dialog where text files can be chosen.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>fixwidthratio</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>fixwidthratio</m>, followed by a floating-point number, sets the ratio of the box 
			to the width of the text when the user chooses <b>Fix Width</b> from the Object menu. The default 
			value is 1.0. A value of 1.1 would make boxes wider than they needed to be, and a value of 0.9 
			would make boxes narrower than they need to be.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getdefaultpatcherheight</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getdefaultpatcherheight</m> followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
			<o>receive</o> object, causes Max to report the current default patcher height in pixels 
			to the named <o>receive</o> object (See also the <m>setdefaultpatcherheight</m> 
			message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getdefaultpatcherwidth</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getdefaultpatcherwidth</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
			<o>receive</o> object, causes Max to report the current default patcher width in pixels 
			to the named <o>receive</o> object (See also the <m>setdefaultpatcherwidth</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getenablepathcache</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getenablepathcache</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a <o>receive</o> 
			object, will report whether the path cache is enabled to the named <o>receive</o> object. 
			(See also the <m>enablepathcache</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getenablerefresh</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Macintosh only.) The word <m>getenablerefresh</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name 
			of a <o>receive</o> object, will report whether enhanced refresh is enabled to the 
			named <o>receive</o> object. (See also the <m>enablerefresh</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>geteventinterval</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>geteventinterval</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a <o>receive</o> 
			object, will report the event interval to the named <o>receive</o> object. (See also the 
			<m>seteventinterval</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getfixwidthratio </m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getfixwidthratio</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a <o>receive</o> 
			object, reports the current fix with ratio value to the named <o>receive</o> object. (See 
			also the <m>fixwidthratio</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getpollthrottle </m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getpollthrottle</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
			<o>receive</o> object, reports the current poll throttle value to the named 
			<o>receive</o> object. (See also the <m>setpollthrottle</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getqueuethrottle</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getqueuethrottle</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of 
			a <o>receive</o> object, causes Max to report the current queue throttle 
			value to the named <o>receive</o> object. (See also the <m>setqueuethrottle</m> 
			message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getrefreshrate</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Macintosh only) The word <m>getrefreshrate</m>, followed by a symbol used as 
			the name of a <o>receive</o> object, causes Max to report the current refresh 
			rate in Hertz to the named <o>receive</o> object. (See also the <m>setrefreshrate</m> 
			message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getruntime </m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getruntime</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
			<o>receive</o> object,sends a 1 to the named <o>receive</o> object if the 
			current version of Max is a runtime version, and a 0 if not.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getsleep </m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getsleep</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
			<o>receive</o> object, causes Max to report the sleep time to the named 
			<o>receive</o> object. (See also the <m>setsleep</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getslop </m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getslop</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
			<o>receive</o> object, reports the scheduler slop value to the named 
			<o>receive</o> object. (See also the <m>setslop message</m> to Max.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>getsysqelemthrottle</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getqueuethrottle</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of 
			a <o>receive</o> object, reports the maximum number of patcher UI update events 
			processed at a time to the named <o>receive</o> object. (See also the <m>setsysqelemthrottle</m> message to Max.)
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>getsystem</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getsystem</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
			<o>receive</o> object, will report the name of the system (macintosh 
			or windows) to the named <o>receive</o> object. 
		</bodytext>
 
 		<header2>
			<m>getversion</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>getversion</m>, followed by a symbol used as the name of a 
    	    <o>receive</o> object, will report the Max version number 
    	    (e.g. 6.1.3 is reported as 1300) to the named <o>receive</o> object.  
		</bodytext>
        
		<header2>
			<m>hidecursor</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Hides the cursor if it is visible.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>hidemenubar</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Hides the menu bar. Although the pull-down menus are not available when the 
			menu bar is hidden, menu shortcut (accelerator) keys continue to work.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>htmlref</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>htmlref</m>, followed by an object name as a symbol, looks for 
			a file called <i>&lt;object-name&gt;</i>.html in the search path. If found, 
			a web browser is opened to view the page.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>interval</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>interval</m>, followed by a number from 1 to 20, sets the timing 
			interval of Max's internal scheduler in milliseconds. The default value is 1. 
			This message only affects the scheduler when Overdrive is on and scheduler 
			in audio interrupt (available with MSP) is off. (When using scheduler in 
			audio interrupt mode the signal vector size determines the scheduler interval.) 
			Larger scheduler intervals can improve CPU efficiency on slower computer 
			models at the expense of timing accuracy. 
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>launchbrowser</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>launchbrowser</m>, followed by a URL as a symbol, opens a web 
			browser to view the URL. For example:
		</bodytext>

		<bodytext>
			<i>; max launchbrowser http://www.cycling74.com</i>
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			<m>maxcharheightforsubpixelantialiasing</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>maxcharheightforsubpixelantialiasing</m>, followed by a number,
				sets a threshold font size (in points) for native subpixel aliasing.
				Since the look of subpixel antialiasing may be undesirable when working with
				large fonts as compared to regular antialiasing, this attribute lets you
				specify a threshold font size; if a font is larger than the specified
				size, it will be rendered using regular rather than subpixel antialiasing.
				<br />
				Note that Max honors your computer's system preferences - Max won't use
				subpixel aliasing if you've disabled it for your system.
				Setting this attribute value to zero  value is 0 will always use regular 
				antialiasing, and setting a very high value will always use subpixel 
				antialiasing (unless it is disabled in system preferences).
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>maxinwmenu</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			When using the runtime version of Max *and* an active custom <o>menubar</o> object, <m>maxinwmenu</m>, followed by the number 1, 
			will place an item called Status in the Windows menu, allowing users to see the 
			Max window (labeled Status in the runtime version). When <m>maxinwmenu</m> is followed 
			by 0 the menu item is not present. The default is for the Status item to be present in 
			the Windows menu.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>maxwindow</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Displays the Max Window. If the Max window if not currently open, the window will be displayed.
			If the window is currently open, it will bring it to the front.
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>midi</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>midi</m>, followed by a variable-length message, allows messages to be sent 
			to configure the system MIDI object. The following is a list of the available options: 
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>midilist</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Prints the names of all current MIDI devices in the Max window. (See also MIDI 
			Messages to Max, above.)
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>nativetextrendering</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>nativetextrendering</m>, followed by a zero or one,
				toggles between using JUCE font rendering (0) and the platform-native
				font rendering for your computer (1) when displaying text in Max.
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>notypeinfo</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Macintosh) The word <m>notypeinfo</m>, followed by zero or one, sets whether Max saves files 
			with traditional Mac OS four-character type information. By default, Max does save 
			this information in files. 
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>objectfile</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>objectfile</m>, followed by two symbols that specify an object name and a 
			file name, creates a mapping between the external object and its filename. For example, 
			the <o>*~</o> object is in a file called <i>times~</i> so at startup Max executes the 
			command <m>max objectfile *~ times~</m>.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>openfile</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>openfile</m>, followed by two symbols that specify an reference name and 
			a file name or path name, attempts to open the patcher with the specified name. If 
			successful, the patcher is associated with the reference symbol, which can be passed 
			as argument to the <m>buildcollective</m>, <m>buildplugin</m>, and <m>closefile</m> messages to Max. 
			The <m>openfile</m> message is intended for batch <!-- plug-in or  -->collective building.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>paths</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			List the current search paths in the Max window. There is a button in the File Preferences 
			window that does this.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>portabbrev</m><space/><i>&lt;innum / outnum&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;abbrev&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			<i>innum</i> specifies an input port, <i>outnum</i> specifies an output port, <i>portname</i> 
			is the name of the port as a single symbol (i.e. It is necessary to use double quotes). 
			An <i>abbrev</i> value is 0 for no abbrev (- in menu), 1 for 'a' and 26 for 'z'.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>portenable</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;0/1&gt;</i> 
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Enables (1) or disables (0) the port specified by <i>portname</i>. All ports are enabled 
			by default.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>portoffset</m><space/><i>&lt;innum / outnum&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;offset&gt;</i> 
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Similar to <m>portabbrev</m>, but offset is the channel offset added to identify input 
			or output ports when a MIDI object can send to or receive from multiple ports by channel 
			number. Must be a multiple of 16 (e.g. <m>max midi portoffset innum PortA 16</m> sets the 
			channel offset for PortA device to 16).
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>preempt</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>preempt</m>, followed by a one (on) or zero (off), toggles Overdrive mode.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>pupdate</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>pupdate</m>, followed by two integer values that specify horizontal and 
			vertical position, moves the mouse cursor to that global location.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>quit</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Quits the Max application; equivalent to choosing <m>Quit</m> from the File menu. 
			If there are unsaved changes to open files, and you haven't sent Max the <m>clean</m> 
			message, Max will ask whether to save changes.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>refresh</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Causes all Max windows to be updated.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>refreshrate</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Macintosh only) The word <m>setrefreshrate</m>, followed by a number, sets the rate, 
			in frames per second, at which the visual display is updated. On Macintosh systems, the rate 
			at which the screen is refreshed is unrelated to the rate at which you change its contents. 
			Better visual performance can be achieved - at the cost of a slight performance decrease 
			in Jitter, and little or no performance decrease for audio processing - by specifying a 
			higher frame rate. When enabled using the <m>enablerefresh 1</m> message, the default rate is 
			28.57 FPS. Refresh enable is off by default.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>runtime</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>runtime</m>, followed by a zero or one and a message, executes the message if 
			the current version of Max is a runtime version (1) or non-runtime (0).
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>sendinterval</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>sendinterval</m>, followed by a symbol, sends the current scheduler interval to 
			the <o>receive</o> object named by the symbol.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>sendapppath</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>sendapppath</m>, followed by a symbol, sends a symbol with the path of the Max 
			application to the <o>receive</o> object named by the symbol. 
		</bodytext>
			
		<header2>
			<m>setdefaultpatcherheight</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setdefaultpatcherheight</m>, followed by an integer value greater than 100, 
			sets the default patcher height in pixels.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>setdefaultpatcherwidth</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setdefaultpatcherwidth</m>, followed by an integer value greater than 100, 
			sets the default patcher width in pixels.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>seteventinterval</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>seteventinterval</m>, followed by an integer value, sets the time between invocations 
			of the event-level timer (The default value is 2 milliseconds). The event-level timer handles 
			low priority tasks like drawing user interface updates and playing movies.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>setmirrortoconsole</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setmirrortoconsole</m>, followed by a 1 or 0, turns on or off (default is 0, off) mirroring of 
			Max window posts to the system console.  The system console is available on the Mac using Console.app, or on
			Windows using the DbgView program (free download from Microsoft).
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>setsleep</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setsleep</m>, followed by a number, sets the time between calls to get the next 
			system event, in 60ths of a second. The default value is 2.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>setpollthrottle</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setpollthrottle</m>, followed by an integer, sets the maximum number of events 
			the scheduler executes each time it is called (The default value is 20). Setting this value 
			lower may decrease accuracy of timing at the expense of efficiency.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>setqueuethrottle </m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setqueuethrottle</m>, followed by an integer value, sets the maximum number of events 
			handled at low-priority each time the low-priority queue handler is called (The default value 
			is 2). Changing this value may affect the responsiveness of the user interface.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>setslop</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setslop</m>, followed by a floating-point value, sets the scheduler slop 
			value - the amount of time a scheduled event can be earlier than the current time 
			before the time of the event is adjusted to match the current time. The default value is 
			25 milliseconds.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>setsysqelemthrottle</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
				The word <m>setsysqelemthrottle</m>, followed by a number, sets the maximum number 
				of patcher UI update events to process at a time. Lower values can lead to more 
				processing power available to other low-priority Max processes, and higher values 
				make the user interface more responsive (especially when using many bpatchers).
		</bodytext>
		
		<header2>
			<m>showcursor</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Shows the cursor if it is hidden.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>showmenubar</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Shows the menu bar after it has been hidden with <m>hidemenubar</m>.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>size</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Prints the number of symbols in the symbol table in the Max window. 
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>system</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>system</m>, followed by the name of an Operating System (windows or macintosh) 
			and a message, will execute the message if Max is running on the named OS.
		</bodytext>
        
		<header2>
			<m>useslowbutcompletesearching</m>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>useslowbutcompletesearching</m>, followed by a one (on) or zero (off), toggles
            complete file searching. When enabled, it causes files not found in Max's cache of the search 
            path to be searched in the file system. This is necessary only in extremely rare cases 
            where the file cache does not update properly. One such case is copying a file into the 
            search path using a version of the Mac OS prior to 10.5.5 over a network. This option 
            may cause patcher files to be loaded more slowly. The setting defaults to off with each 
            launch of the application, and is not stored in the user's preferences. 
            <m>useslowbutcompletesearching 0</m> turns the setting off.
		</bodytext>
        
		<header2>
			MIDI Configuration Messages
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Messages for creating new MIDI ports:
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM createoutport</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;drivername&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Creates a new port for the specified driver. On Windows, the only driver that supports creating new ports is  <m>midi_dm</m>, which creates a new port to talk to the <link type="vignette" module="core" name="dls_synthesizer">DLS synthesizer</link>. On the Mac, specifying the <m>coremidi</m> driver name creates a virtual output port you can use to communicate with other MIDI applications, while specifying the <m>augraph</m> driver name creates another port exclusively assigned to the <link type="vignette" module="core" name="dls_synthesizer">DLS synthesizer</link>.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM deleteoutport</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;drivername&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Deletes a port created with the <m>createoutport</m> message. <i>drivername</i>  and <i>portname</i> should be the same as the arguments originally passed to <m>createoutport</m>.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM driver loadbank</m><space/><i>&lt;filename&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Loads a type 1 or 2 DLS Bank, where <i>filename</i> is the name of an existing DLS 
			bank file, and <i>portname</i> is the name of the port that will use this bank. 
			If <i>portname</i> is omitted, all DLS ports will use the bank. On Mac OS X, the 
			folder <i>/Library/Audio/Sounds/Banks</i> is added to the search path when looking 
			for a DLS bank file.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM driver loadbank 0</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Loads the DLS default GM Bank.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM driver reverb</m><space/><i>&lt;1/0&gt; &lt;portname&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Turns reverb on or off. By default reverb is off in both augraph and midi_dm.
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM driver latency</m><space/><i>&lt;time&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(midi_dm only) Sets the MIDI Output Latency where <i>time</i> is a value in 
			milliseconds and <i>portname</i> is the port that is set to this value. 
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM inportinfo</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;receive name&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<header2>
			<m>;#SM outportinfo</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;receive name&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The <m>inportinfo</m> and <m>outportinfo</m> messages send information about MIDI 
			ports to named <o>receive</o> objects. The information is contained in an 
			<m>infolist</m> message with the following arguments:
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			the port's name (symbol) 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			the port's driver name (symbol) 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			the port's unique ID (int) 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			the port's abbreviation (int) 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			the port's channel offset (int) 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			whether the port is enabled or disabled (one if enabled, zero if disabled) 
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			whether the port was created dynamically (one if yes, zero if no) 
		</bodytext>

		<header2>
			<m>;#SM createinport</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;drivername&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			(Mac only) Adds a virtual MIDI input port, where <i>portname</i> is the 
			name you assign to the port, and <i>drivername</i> should be set to <m>coremidi</m>. Other MIDI applications can send messages to Max using this port.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			<m>;#SM deleteinport</m><space/><i>&lt;portname&gt;</i><space/><i>&lt;drivername&gt;</i>
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			Deletes a port created with the <m>createinport</m> message. <i>drivername</i>  and <i>portname</i> should be the same as the arguments originally passed to <m>createinport</m>.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Ports created with the <m>createoutport</m> and <m>createinport</m> messages are not saved as a part of your MIDI setup preferences.
		</bodytext>
</vignette>
