<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Controlling MSP with Messages">
			<header1>
			Controlling MSP with Messages
			</header1>
		<bodytext>
			You can control MSP using the <o>message</o> box object. Normally, 
			the <o>message</o> box contains an object, and you click on it or replace a variable 
			typed into the <o>message</o> box to send a message via a patch cord to another 
			Max object. However, if the message in a <o>message</o> box begins with a semicolon (;) 
			followed by the word <m>dsp</m>, any message which follows will be sent directly 
			to the Max application itself, just as though there were a <o>receive</o> object named "dsp".
		</bodytext>			
	<br /><space />
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			Sending a message to the Max application
		</header2>
			<ul>
			<li>
			Add a <o>message</o> box to your Patcher, and type in a semicolon and the
			word dsp (<m>; dsp</m>), 
			followed by the message you want to send. Your message box can 
			contain variables (e.g. <m>: dsp sigvs $1</m>).
			<br />
			You don't ned to connect the message box to anything, although you may want to 
			connect something to the inlet of the message box to supply a message 
			argument or trigger it from a <o>loadbang</o> object to configure MSP 
			signal processing parameters when your patcher file is opened.
			</li>
			</ul>
		<bodytext>
			When you click on the <o>message</o> box or send it a <m>bang</m> or a value, 
			the message will be sent to the Max application.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br /><space />
		<bodytext>
			Here is listing of the messages you can send to the Max application using this technique:
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			cpulimit
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>cpulimit</m>, followed by a number in the range 0-100, sets a utilization limit for the 
			CPU. Above this limit, MSP will not process audio vectors until the utilization 
			comes back down, causing a click. If the cpu limit is set to either 0 or 100, there will be
			no limit checking done.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			inremap
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>inremap</m>, followed by two numbers that specify a physical device input
			channel number and a logical input channel number, maps the physical device to the logical
			input channel.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			iovs
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>iovs</m>, followed by a number that is a power of 2, sets the I/O 
			vector size.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			open
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>open</m> opens the Audio Status window.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			optimize
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>optimize</m>, followed by a zero or one, turns Altivec optimization on (1) or off (0).
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			outremap
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>outremap</m>, followed by two numbers that specify a logical device output
			channel number and a physical output channel number, maps the logical device to the physical
			output channel.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			set
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>set</m>, followed by a zero or one, turns the audio on (1) or off (0). It
			is equivalent to clicking on a <o>ezadc~</o> or <o>ezdac~</o> object.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			setdriver
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>setdriver</m>, followed by a number, sets a new audio driver
			based on its index into the currently generated menu of drivers created by the 
			<o>adstatus</o> driver object. If the word <m>setdriver</m> is followed by a symbol
			that names a valid driver, the new driver is selected by name. An additional symbol
			argument may be used to specify a "subdriver" (e.g., ASIO drivers use ASIO as the
			name of the driver and PCI-324 as a subdriver name that specifies a specific device).
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			sigvs
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>sigvs</m>, followed by a number that is a power of 2, sets the I/O 
			signal vector size.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			sr
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>sr</m>, followed by a number, sets a new sampling rate In Hertz.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			start
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>start</m> turns the audio on.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			status
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>status</m> opens the Audio Status window.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			stop
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>stop</m> turns the audio off.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			takeover
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>takeover</m>, followed by a zero or one, turns Scheduler in Audio Interrupt mode on (1) or off (0).
			It is equivalent to clicking on the Scheduler in Overdrive checkbox in the Audio Status window.
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			timecode
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>timecode</m> followed by a zero or one, starts (1) or stops (0) 
			timecode reading by any audio drivers that support the feature (ASIO 2).
		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			wclose
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The word <m>wclose</m> closes the Audio Status window.
		</bodytext>				
</vignette>
