<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Object Explorer">
	<header1>
	The Object Explorer
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The Object Explorer replaces the older Max Object Palette. It is a searchable and categorized listing of Max, MSP, and Jitter object as well as all of the patchers located in your 
			<link anchor="searchpath" module="core" name="file_preferences_window" type="vignette">search path</link>.
			It adds a number of novel ways for browsing and discovering Max objects to the earlier object-box-based 
			search methods, and adds an the integrated search field and
			<link anchor="autocompletion" module="core" name="patcher_window" type="vignette">autocompletion</link>
			features you’ll find in several places in the Max interface. As before, you can patch directly from the Object Explorer by dragging objects into a patcher window.
	</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Viewing the Object Explorer
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
		There are several ways of displaying the Object Explorer.
	</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the Show Object Explorer button in the 
			toolbar 
			of an unlocked Patcher window.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click on the 
			Sidebar
			button in the 
			toolbar 
			of an unlocked Patcher window. The Object Explorer will be displayed in the opened Sidebar panel.
		</li>
			<li>
			Double-click anywhere in the blank space in an unlocked Patcher window. 
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			You can also type the letter "p" (<b>P</b>alette).
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			The Object Explorer displays icons for the objects available to you in Max sorted by their category.
			The precise makeup of the Object Explorer will vary based on what
			objects you have installed, but the
			objects in each category are listed in alphabetical order.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<header2>
		Navigating the Object Explorer
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		You can scroll the Object Explorer vertically to see the full listing of categories of Max
		objects and their contents. <i><b>Note:</b> The scroll bar is only visible while scrolling or 
		when you position your cursor along the right-hand edge of the Object Explorer window.</i>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		Every Max object belongs to a category. Each category has a disclosure triangle to you can use to show or
		hide its contents.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/object_explorer_2.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The upper portion of the Object Explorer contains a number of buttons and menus you can use to 
		refine your searches and investigations.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Exploring Objects by Kind
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			The Show bar of the Object Explorer includes a number of view selectors that allow you to 
			look for objects and Max patches according to their type or use.
	</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_show_bar1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
		<li>
			<b>UI Objects</b> will display user interface objects only
		</li>
		<li>
			<b>Max</b>,
			<b>MSP</b>,
			and
			<b>Jitter</b>
			view selectors will display only Max, MSP, or Jitter objects. 
		</li>
		<li>
			The <b>Patchers</b> view selector is a menu that displays selection options that correspond to different kinds of Max patches that may be stored in your
			search path. Selections are availble for
			different varieties of
			abstractions,
			(sorted according to their content)
			bpatchers,
			and special-purpose patchers associated with the Max 
			gen
			objects.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_show_bar2.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on a view selector in the Object Explorer to show a subset of Max objects.
			The display will update to show only those objects in each of the category tabs.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_show_bar3.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Exploring Objects by Category
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
		The Object Explorer also lets you refine your search for Max objects by their 
		category using the Go To Category/Search bar. The menu items available under 
		the Go To Category menu varies and is determined by what set of objects are 
		currently visible in the object explorer as set by the Show bar's view 
		selector buttons.
	</bodytext>
		<bodytext>		
		The <b>Go To</b> Category menu always contains a <b>Show All</b> item. Selecting this item will
		will show all categories in the Object Explorer related to the Show Bar's view selector settings.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<b>Note:</b> The list of categories available under the categories menu is determined by what set of objects 
		are currently visible in the object explorer - categories are only available for visible objects and that is 
		determined by the state of the show buttons and filter field settings.
	</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the down arrow to show the menu of Category choices currently available.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_bar2.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			When you release the mouse, the Object Explorer will close all categories <i>except</i> the one you've selected. 
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_bar3.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bodytext>
			The Show bar of the Object Explorer includes a number of view selectors that allow you to 
			look for objects and Max patches according to their type or use.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext><b>Note:</b> The list of categories available under the categories menu is determined by what set of objects 
		are currently visible in the object explorer - categories are only available for visible objects and that is 
		determined by the state of the show buttons and filter field settings.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/object_explorer_show_bar1.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext><b>UI Objects</b> will display user interface objects only
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext><b>Max</b>,
			<b>MSP</b>,
			and
			<b>Jitter</b>
			view selectors will display only Max, MSP, or Jitter objects. 
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <b>Patchers</b> view selector is a menu that displays selection options that correspond to different kinds of Max patches that may be stored in your
			search path. Selections are availble for
			different varieties of
			abstractions,
			(sorted according to their content)
			bpatchers,
			and special-purpose patchers associated with the Max 
			gen
			objects.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Exploring Objects by Category
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
		The Object Explorer also lets you refine your search for Max objects by their category.
		The <b>Go To</b> category menu will close all categories in the Object Explorer <i>except</i> the one you've selected.
	</bodytext>
		<bodytext><b>Note:</b> The list of categories available under the categories menu is determined by what set of objects 
		are currently visible in the object explorer - categories are only available for visible objects and that is 
		determined by the state of the show buttons and filter field settings.
	</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the down arrow button to the right of Go To Category and make a selection from the menu.
			When you release the mouse, the Object Explorer will show only the category you have selected.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_bar2.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Searching the Object Explorer
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
		The Object Explorer includes a search window you can use to narrow down your search or to browse for objects.
	</bodytext>
		<bodytext><b>Note:</b> The search window returns matches based on the current Explorer settings based on the
		Go To Category and Show settings. You can changes these settings as you type to direct your search.
	</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click in the Object Explorer's Search window to get a cursor and start typing. As you do,
			the object explorer will modify its display to suggest objects you should investigate further.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/object_explorer_bar_search.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
</vignette>
