<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Parameter attributes in Max">
	<header1>
		Parameter attributes in Max
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		In order to provide interoperability between the Max and Live 
		application, Max for Live introduced some new attributes
		intended to allow users to include generic Max UI objects (e.g. 
		<o>rslider</o>, 
		<o>multislider</o>
		) as part of a Max for Live device.
		These parameter attributes are available to all Max users, and 
		provide a simple means for saving the initial state of
		any Max/Max for Live UI object in a Max patch in addition to 
		<link module="core" name="live_parameters" type="vignette">their use with Max for Live</link>.
	</bodytext>
	<header2>
		Parameter Data Types
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		Parameters used in Max for Live can be one of four types: 
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		integer. Note: In Max for Live, integer ranges are 
		restricted to 0 - 255).
	</li>
		<li>
		floating-point.	
	</li>
		<li>
		enum: an enumerated list of items
	</li>
		<li>
		blob: any type of data you can store with a 
		<o>pattr</o> object: single values, lists, or strings.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Setting an initial state for a UI object
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select the UI object and click the Inspector button in the Patcher toolbar 
		to show the object's
		<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>.
	</li>
			<li>
		Locate the Parameter Enable attribute and click in the
		Parameter Mode Enable checkbox. The Inspector will display
		an additional group of attributes.
		<br/>
		<br/>
		Note: If you have selected a Max for Live UI object (e.g.
		<o>live.dial</o>,
		<o>live.sider</o>,
		etc.) Parameter mode is automatically enabled.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/parameter_enable.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Locate the Initial Enable attribute and click in the checkbox to enable it.
	</li>
			<li>
		Enter a value by clicking in Value column for the Initial attribute
		and typing in a value.
	</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<br/>
	<header1>
	Parameter Names
</header1>
	<bodytext>
	Max provides several ways to name a parameter in a device, each
	of which is an
	<link module="core" name="attributes_intro" type="vignette">Attribute</link>
	that can be set using an object's 
	<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>.
	These names can be set separately or linked together, and they serve several
	useful purposes.
</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		The <m>Scripting Name</m> attribute can be used to identify a UI object
		when used in conjunction with the Max <o>pattr</o> preset objects. When
		a UI object has a scripting name set, it will automatically appear in the
		<o>pattrstorage</o> object's inventory of parameter names when you add an
		<o>autopattr</o> object to your Max patch as described in the 
		<link module="max" name="pattrchapter02" type="tutorial">pattr Chapter 2</link>.		
		Max tutorial.
	</li>
		<li>
		The <m>Long Name</m> and <m>Short Name</m> attributes are 
		<link anchor="m4lnames" module="core" name="live_parameters" type="vignette">commonly used when working with Max for Live</link>.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<header1>
	Ordering Initial Value Recall
</header1>
	<bodytext>
		The Order attribute, can be used to set the order in which parameters
		are recalled and set when a patch is opened. By default, all attributes 
		are recalled sequentially/at one time. By setting an attribute to have a 
		lower order number, you can recall initial parameter values in complex 
		patches whose initial values may need to be calculated based on initial 
		values so that the dependencies are preserved.
		<br/>
		<br/>
		Note: the order in which initial values are set for attributes having
		the same order value is indeterminate.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Setting the initialization order a UI object
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select the UI object and click the Inspector button in the Patcher toolbar 
		to show the object's
		<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>.
	</li>
			<li>
		Locate the Parameter Enable attribute and click in the
		Parameter Mode Enable checkbox. The Inspector will display
		an additional group of attributes.
		<br/>
		<br/>
		Note: If you have selected a Max for Live UI object (e.g.
		<o>live.dial</o>,
		<o>live.sider</o>,
		etc.) Parameter mode is automatically enabled.
	</li>
			<li>
		Enter a value by clicking in Value column for the Order attribute
		and typing in a value. Higher numbers will be recalled and initialized
		first (the default is 0 - first priority).
	</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<br/>
</vignette>
