<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Multiple Views of a Patcher">
	<header1>
	Multiple Views of a Patcher
	</header1>
<bodytext>
	Working with multiple views of a patcher can be useful for a number of tasks:
</bodytext>
<ul>
	<li>Using patching and <link type="vignette" module="core" name="presentation_mode">presentation mode</link> simultaneously, so you can see the relationship between objects in each mode.</li>
	<li>Editing a patcher inside a <o>bpatcher</o></li>
	<li>Maintaining window with a large patcher zoomed out provide an overview while working at a higher resolution on details.</li>
</ul>
<bodytext>
	It's important to note that views are part of the <i>editing environment</i> of Max, not the runtime environment. For example, you cannot save a patcher so that it will open in multiple views.
</bodytext>
<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Creating a new view of a patcher
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Make the desired patcher the active window.
		</li>
		<li>
			Click on the Patcher Windows icon in the patcher window toolbar and select "New View" from the pull-down menu.
		</li>
		<li>
			A new view of the patcher will open, usually a bit to the right of the existing view. At this point, you can switch the new view to <link type="vignette" module="core" name="presentation_mode">presentation mode</link>, or patching mode, or change its zoom level.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Creating a new view of a bpatcher
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Ctrl (Mac) or Right-Click the bpatcher object in an unlocked patcher.
		</li>
		<li>
			Choose <b>New View of "patchername"</b> from the Object submenu of the contextual menu that appears. ("patchername" will be the name of the patcher inside the <o>bpatcher</o>.)
		</li>
		<li>
			A new view of the patcher will open.
		</li>
		<li>
			If you want to edit the patcher "live" while watching the effect of your changes in the bpatcher, choose <b>Modify Read-Only</b> from the File menu when the new view is the active window.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
