<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Patcher Preferences">
	<header1>
	Patcher Preferences
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			Max remembers many of your working preferences associated with various details of
			working in a Patcher window by storing settings each time you quit the
			application. The first time you use Max, a folder containing your preferences is created.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Some of these preferences are set for things you use often, such as using
			<link anchor="segmented" module="core" name="patch_cords" type="vignette">segmented patch cords</link>
			or
			<link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">providing assistance</link>
			on objects and abstractions you use while patching.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Other parameters involve ways that Max responds to you as you patch.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Scheduler parameter settings may be viewed and set using the
			<link module="core" name="preferences_window" type="vignette">Preferences Window</link>.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Viewing the Patcher Preferences
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences...</b> from the Max menu. The Preferences Window will be shown
		</li>
			<li>
			Locate the <b>Patcher</b> category to show the Patcher preference settings.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Getting information about a Patcher Preferences setting
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Position your cursor over the Setting column of any row in the window. A brief description of
			the setting will be shown in the
			Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
			When Auto Fix Width is checked, Max will automatically adjust the width of
			all object boxes, a comments, or a message boxes to accommodate all the 
			text they contain on a single line.
		</bodytext>
	<a name="overdrive"/>
	<header2>
	About the scheduler settings:
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			When <i>Overdrive</i> is enabled, Max gives priority to timing and MIDI processing
			over screen drawing and user interface tasks such as responding to mouse clicks.
			If you are primarily going to be using Max for MIDI or audio processing, Overdrive
			should be enabled. If you are primarily going to be using Jitter, Overdrive 
			should be disabled.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			For many Max users, Overdrive is the only scheduler parameter that they will ever set.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Enabling/disabling Overdrive
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Overdrive</b> from the Options menu. The Overdrive menu item will
			be checked, and Overdrive will be enabled (the Overdrive Value in the Scheduler
			tab of the Preferences Window will be updated to indicate your choice).
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			To disable Overdrive, choose <b>Overdrive</b> from the Options menu. The menu item
			will be unchecked to indicate that Overdrive is disabled.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext><i>Refresh Rate</i> sets the rate, in Hz., at which Max attempts to update the 
			interface (The actual refresh rate may be higher or lower depending on various 
			application and operating system activities, and overall system load). A lower 
			setting (e.g. 5) means that Max will update the interface more slowly, but run 
			more efficiently, while a higher value (e.g. 60) will mean that the interface 
			is faster and more responsive. The default value is 30 Hz.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Scheduler slop</i> is the amount of time, in milliseconds, the scheduler 
			is permitted to fall behind actual time before correcting the scheduler 
			time to actual time. The scheduler will fall behind actual time if there 
			are more high priority events than can be processed in real time. Scheduler 
			slop prevents the scheduler from backlogging in such a case with some 
			slop—a threshold. Typically some amount of slop is desired so that high 
			priority events (like a metronome) will maintain long term temporal accuracy 
			despite small temporal deviations. A lower setting (e.g. 1) results in greater 
			short term accuracy, while a higher value (e.g. 100) will mean that the 
			scheduler is more accurate in the long term. The default value is 25 milliseconds.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Sleep Interval</i> sets the amount of time, in milliseconds, that 
			the low priority thread sleeps between servicing the low priority event 
			queue (Low priority events include user interface events, graphics 
			operations, reading files from disk, and other expensive operations that 
			would otherwise cause timing problems for the scheduler). A lower setting (e.g. 1) 
			results in greater responsiveness, while a higher value (e.g. 20) will mean 
			that more time is available for other applications. The default value is 
			2 milliseconds.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			When <i>Enable Refresh</i> is checked (on), the screen will be refreshed 
			at the rate set by the Refresh Rate parameter. This can help improve visual 
			performance on some machines.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Poll Throttle</i> sets the number of events processed per servicing 
			of the scheduler's high priority event queue (High priority events include 
			MIDI, events generated by <o>metro</o>, <o>tempo</o>, <o>line</o>, <o>delay</o>, <o>pipe</o>, <o>snapshot~</o>, 
			and other scheduler based objects). A lower setting (e.g. 1) means less 
			event clumping, while a higher value (e.g. 100) will result in less of 
			an event backlog. The default value is 20 events.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Event Interval</i> is the rate, in milliseconds, at which Max attempts 
			to update the interface. The actual refresh rate may be higher or lower 
			depending on various application and operating system activities, and 
			overall system load. A lower setting (e.g. 1) will provide greater accuracy in terms of interface updates, while a higher value (e.g. 20) will result in less CPU usage. The default value is 2 ms events.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Queue Throttle</i> sets the number of events processed per servicing 
			of the low priority event queue (Low priority events include user 
			interface events, graphics operations, reading files from disk, and 
			other expensive operations that would otherwise cause timing problems 
			for the scheduler). A lower setting (e.g. 1) means less event clumping, 
			while a higher value (e.g. 100) will result in less of an event backlog. 
			The default value is 10 events.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Changing the Scheduler Settings
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences...</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the 
			Options menu (Windows) to show the Preferences Window.
		</li>
			<li>
			Locate the <b>Scheduler</b> category to show the Scheduler settings.
		</li>
			<li>
			Double-click on the Value column for the Setting you want to change 
			to show a cursor and text box.
		</li>
			<li>
			Type the new value, followed by a carriage return. The new scheduler 
			value will be set.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
