<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="The Patch Cord Menu">
	<header1>
	Patch Cord Contextual Menu
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		The Patch Cord Contextual Menu makes your patching life easier by providing you quick 
		access to a number of useful patching activities with a click of the mouse. You can
		use the menu to quickly align, delete and route connections, create or delete
		<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">watchpoints</link> 
		when debugging a patch, and even disable/enable a selected connection.
	</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Viewing the Patch Cord Contextual Menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Hover over a patchcord to highlight it and display the menu button, 
			and click on the menu button to display the contextual menu.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/patchcordmenu_1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
			The Patch Cord Contextual Menu displays
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Menu items that let you delete, align, and route a patch cord or remove its segments.
		</li>
		<li>
			Menu items that let you add or remove
			Monitor
			or 
			Break 
			watchpoints to the connection, and show/hide the watchpoint.
		</li>
		<li>
			Menu items for enabling and disabling the patch cord connection.
		</li>
		<li>
			A menu item to set the color of the patch cord.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Getting information from the Patch Cord Contextual Menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Hover over a patchcord to highlight it and display the menu button, and click on the menu button to display the contextual menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			As you move your cursor over any menu listings, a description of
			the message will appear in the
			Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			Patching from the Patch Cord Contextual Menu
		</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Delete</b> from the menu to delete the currently selected patch cord.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Align</b> from the menu to align the currently selected patch cord.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Route Patch Cords</b> from the menu to create a patch cord path that routes the connection to avoid overlapping external objects in your patch.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Remove All Segments</b> from the menu to remove any and all segments in the selected patch cord.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Color....</b> from the menu to open the
			<link module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">Color Picker</link>
			and choose a color for the currently selected patch cord.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			Debugging with the Patch Cord Contextual Menu
		</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Add Watchpoint - Monitor</b> from the menu to add a
			<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">monitor watchpoint</link>
			to the currently selected patch cord.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Add Watchpoint - Break</b> from the menu to add a
			<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">monitor watchpoint</link>
			to the currently selected patch cord.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Remove Watchpoint</b> from the menu to remove any 
			breakpoints associated with the currently selected patch cord.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Show Watchpoints</b> from the menu to display the 
			<link anchor="watchpointswindow" module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">Watchpoints Window</link>
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			Disabling/Enabling patch cords
		</header2>
		<bodytext>
			You can use the Patch Cord Contextual menu to disable a patch cord - to prevent it from sending data to the object to which it is connected.
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Hover over a patchcord to highlight it and display the menu button, and click on the menu button to display the contextual menu.
		</li>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Disable Patch Cord</b> from the contextual menu. The patch cord will be greyed out and display a
			button indicating that it is disabled.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/disabled_patchcord.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			Choose <b>Enable Patch Cord</b> from the contextual menu to re-enable data transfer.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
</vignette>
