<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Patching Settings">
	<header1>
	Setting Patching preferences
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Patching</i> category of the Max Preferences window
			contains a listing of parameter settings related to how
			Max behaves as you use it to create patches.Max's
			behavior as you patch (e.g.
			<link anchor="segmented" module="core" name="patch_cords" type="vignette">segmented patch cords</link>,
			enabling
			<link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Assistance</link>
			in a patcher, etc.), and settings that control how the Max interface
			responds to you (e.g., auto fix width, 
			<link anchor="autocompletion" module="core" name="patcher_window" type="vignette">autocompletion</link>, 
			etc.)
		</bodytext>
	<header2>
	Preferences for working with Max object boxes
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			There are several preferences you can set that will control the way that
			Max object boxes behave while you're creating them, and how you'd like them
			to behave while you edit the box content and type text into them (in both patching
			and
			Presentation Mode.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			You can enable or disable 
			<link anchor="autocompletion" module="core" name="patcher_window" type="vignette">autocompletion</link>
			by clicking in the Object Box Autocompletion checkbox in the Patching pane of
			the Preferences Window.
		</bodytext>
	<a name="defaultboxbehavior"/>
	<bodytext>
			You can change the way that Max behaves when you click on an object so that
			you can begin editing the text in a box as soon as you click on an object
			by clicking the Edit Box on Click and Typing Automatically Edits
			Selected Box checkboxes in the Patching pane of
			the Preferences Window.
			You can enable or disable these features independently for both patcher and
			Presentation Mode.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			When Select Text on Click is enabled, clicking on a text object box selects 
			it immediately for editing. When disabled, clicking on a text object box 
			selects the entire box instead of selecting the text inside.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			When Typing Automatically Edits Selected Box is enabled, typing begins 
			to edit an entirely selected box immediately. When disabled, typing does 
			not affect an entirely selected box until you click it again to select 
			the text.
		</bodytext>
	<header2>
	Preferences for how object boxes are displayed
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			While you can easily change the size of a Max object box by clicking and dragging
			its resizing handles, you may find it useful to set your preferences so that boxes
			are automatically resized at a fixed percentage size based on the text you type into 
			them.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			When the Auto Fix Width is enabled, Max will automatically adjust the width of
			all object boxes, a comments, or a message boxes to accommodate all the text 
			they contain on a single line.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			When performing this automatic resizing, Max sets the proportion of the text line 
			length used when autosizing using the Fix Width Ratio setting found in the 
			Patching pane of the Preferences Window.
		</bodytext>
	<header2>
	Grid preferences for the Max application
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			Although you can control the presence and size of Max visual patching grid in
			individual windows using the 
			Patcher Inspector,
			you may want to set these parameters to automatically be set whenever you launch
			Max and start patching in new patcher windows.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="gridonstartup"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Viewing the Grid on startup
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences...</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) 
			to show the Preferences Window. Click on the Patching tab in 
			the Preferences Window.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click in the checkbox in the Value column for the Show Grid (default for new patchers) setting. The
			next time you launch Max, you will see the grid in every unlocked Patcher window.
			on startup.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="defaultgridsize"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Setting the default grid size
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Patcher Inspector</b> from the View menu to show the Patcher Inspector.
		</li>
			<li>
			Double-click in the Value column for the Grid Size setting to show a
			cursor and text box. You can type new horizontal and vertical values into the
			text box and type a carriage return to set the alignment grid size.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="defaultsnaptogrid"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Enabling Snap to Grid on startup
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences...</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) 
			to show the Preferences Window. Click on the Patching tab in 
			the Preferences Window.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click in the checkbox in the Value column for the Snap to Grid (default for new patchers) setting. The
			next time you launch Max, the Snap to Grid feature will automatically be enabled.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<header2>
	Real-time patching behavior settings
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			You can choose to use straight, segmented, or curved patch cords
			as a default setting as you patch with Max. Max uses curved and
			unsegmented patch cords by default.
			<br/>
			In addition, you can also avail yourself of the entertaining feature that lets
			you control the rate at which objects appear and disappear from an unlocked patcher
			window as you add or remove them, and also control similar timing for scrolling
			automation.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<a name="curvedpatchcords"/>
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Working with curved patch cords
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences...</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) 
			to show the Preferences Window and locate the the Patching category in 
			the Preferences Window.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click the checkbox in the Value column for the Curved Patch Cords setting to disable
			or enable curved patch cords. The item will be checked, your patches will automatically
			update themselves to use your patching selection, and your curved patch cord selection
			will automatically be enabled as the new default setting.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<a name="segmentedpatchcords"/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Enabling patch cord behavior at startup
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences...</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) 
			to show the Preferences Window and locate the the Patching category in 
			the Preferences Window.
		</li>
			<li>
			If you'd like to work with segmented patch cords as your default setting, 
			click the checkbox in the Value column for the Segmented Patch Cords setting. The menu
			item will be checked, segmented patch cords will automatically be enabled as the new
			default setting.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<header2>
	Fade and scrolling fun
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			To set the default time it will take Max objects to appear and disappear
			when you create them while patching, double-click in the Values column
			of the Box Fade Time or Scroll Animation Time settings to get a text cursor
			and type in a value, in milliseconds.
		</bodytext>
</vignette>
