<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Preferences Window">
	<header1>
	The Preferences Window
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			Max remembers many of your working preferences by storing settings each time you quit the
			application. The first time you use Max, a folder containing your preferences is created.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			On Macintosh, this folder is called “Max 6 Preferences Folder”, and is in the Preferences
			folder inside the <i>Library</i> folder of your home directory. Your preferences are stored in
			a file called <i>maxpreferences.maxpref</i>.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			On Windows, this folder is called “Max 6 Preferences Files”, and its location varies
			according to the name of the user logged in (e.g.
			<i>C:\Documents and Settings\&lt;user&gt;\Application Data\Cycling '74\Max 6 Preferences Files\</i>).
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The Preferences folder is also where Max stores settings you have chosen in the
			<link module="core" name="midi_setup_window" type="vignette">MIDI setup</link>and
				<link module="core" name="file_preferences_window" type="vignette">file preferences</link> windows, as well as the current settings of the Options menu.
		</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Viewing the Preferences Window
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) to show the Preferences Window.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/preferences1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
			The preferences are divided into categories, each of which is associated
			with a category divider in the Presentation Window. Each divider contains a
			disclosure triangle that you can click to hide or reveal the attributes
			associated with the divider.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			You can mouse over an item and look in the
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>
			to see a description of each preference item.
		</bodytext>
	<header2>
	Navigating the Preferences Window
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			The top of the Preferences Window has four view selector tabs that allow you to view
			subsets of preferences that you will probably use often in addition to viewing the 
			entire contents of the window.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>All</i> shows all of the preferences in a single pane.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Basic</i> shows a subset of the commonly accessed preferences, organized by category.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Colors</i> shows a subset of settings associated with colors used in the patching environment.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Recent</i> shows categories that you have recently edited for Max.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="assistance_preferences" type="vignette">Assistance category</link>
			of the Preferences Window shows the settings associated with using the 
			<link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Assistance</link>
			features of Max.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="browser_preferences" type="vignette">Browser category</link>
			of the Preferences Window shows some settings associated with using the 
			<link module="core" name="file_browser" type="vignette">File Browser</link>
			features of Max.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="clue_window_preferences" type="vignette">Clue category</link>
			of the Preferences Window lets you set the colors for the 
			Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="clue_window" type="vignette">Clue Window</link>
			(whose functionality has largely been replaced by the Max 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>
			).
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The 
			<link module="core" name="debugging_preferences" type="vignette">Debugging category</link>
			of the Preferences Window lets you set the behavior of features related to debugging
			your patches -
			<link module="core" name="watchpoints" type="vignette">Watchpoints</link>
			and
			other
			<link module="core" name="tracing_tools" type="vignette">debugging tools</link>.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="font_preferences" type="vignette">Font category</link>
			of the Preferences Window shows the settings for the default font and default size.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="interface_preferences" type="vignette">Interface category</link>
			of the Preferences Window shows some settings how the ways that the Max
			interface works (e.g., truncating floating point numbers automatically).
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="language_preferences" type="vignette">Language category</link>
			lists the currently available language choices.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="mixer_preferences" type="vignette">Mixer category</link>
			lets you set preferences for the behavior of the 
			<link module="core" name="mixer" type="vignette">Mixer</link>
			features of Max. You can.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The
			<link module="core" name="patching_preferences" type="vignette">Patching category</link>
			of the Preferences Window contains a listing of parameters related to Max's
			behavior as you patch (e.g.
			<link anchor="segmented" module="core" name="patch_cords" type="vignette">segmented patch cords</link>,
			enabling
			<link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Assistance</link>
			in a patcher, etc.), and settings that control how the Max interface
			responds to you (e.g., auto fix width, 
			<link anchor="autocompletion" module="core" name="patcher_window" type="vignette">autocompletion</link>, 
			etc.)
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The 
			<link module="core" name="scheduler_settings" type="vignette">Scheduling category</link>
			of the Preferences Window shows the parameters you can use when tuning the performance of Max
			on your system.
		</bodytext>
	<header2>
	About the Window’s columns:
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			The Preferences Window consists of three columns:
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Attribute</i> column can be used to edit and restore attribute settings.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Setting</i> column has the name or a description of each object setting
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			The <i>Value</i> column displays the current value associated with each setting
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Changing the Preferences Window view
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on a view selector in the Preferences Window to show a subset of all the settings.
			To return to the original organization of settings, click on the All tab.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click on the disclosure triangle for a preferences category to hide or reveal the 
			preferences.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Getting information about an Inspector setting
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Position your cursor over the Setting column of any row in the window. A brief description of
			the setting will be shown in the
			Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Changing the value of a Setting
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click in the Value column for a Setting row to select the value you want to change
		</li>
			<li>
			If the value column contains a check box, click in the box to toggle the value
		</li>
			<li>
			If the value column has a set of arrows on the right, it is a pop-up menu.
			Click in the Value column, choose a setting from the pop-up menu, and release.
		</li>
			<li>
			If the value column contains a color display, click in the box to show
			the
			<link module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">Color Picker</link>
			pop-up menu. You can use the swatch to set colors
			or enter them as text.
		</li>
			<li>
			If the value column contains ints, floats, messages, or lists, double-click
			in the box to show a cursor and text box. You can type values into the text
			box and type a carriage return to set the values.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Changing the attribute list order
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on a Setting column. The column will be selected an an arrow will appear on the 
			right side of the column header.
		</li>
			<li>
			Click on the arrow to re-sort the contents for each category of the object Inspector 
			in alphabetical order
		</li>
			<li>
			Click on the left-hand column header to restore the original “default” listing order 
			for all Settings.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
