<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="The Preferences Toolbar">
	<header1>
		The Preferences Toolbar
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>Modify Selected Item</i> button displays a pop-up menu
		of commands for modifying a selected attribute's preference.
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/preferences_toolbar1.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		The <i>Show/Hide Attribute Names</i> button toggles the display
		of an additional column in the Inspector that displays the
		programmatic names for an object's attributes.
	</bodytext>
	<!-- commented out until I find out what's up with the button
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/preferences_toolbar2.png"/>
	</bodytext>
-->
	<header2>
		Working with Attribute Default Values
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		You can use the Modify Selected Item pull-down menu to perform
		several useful tasks when you are editing attributes. You can
		revert to previously set or to default values, set an attribute
		value to match a
		<link module="core" name="ui_defaults" type="vignette">color scheme</link>
		you've created, or revert to the original value of an attribute whose
		value you have
		<link module="core" name="freezing_attributes" type="vignette">frozen</link>.	
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
		Choosing 
		<b>Revert Value</b> from the 
		Modify Selected Item pull-down menu will return the selected 
		attribute to its previous value.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing 
		<b>Set to Default Value</b> from the 
		Modify Selected Item pull-down menu will set the 
		selected attribute to its default value.
	</li>
		<li>	
		Choosing 
		<b>Set to Named Default Value</b> from the 
		Modify Selected Item pull-down menu will return the selected attribute to the 
		default setting for the currently loaded 
		<link module="core" name="ui_defaults" type="vignette">color scheme</link>.
	</li>
		<li>
		Choosing
		<b>Set to Frozen Value</b>
		from the Modify Selected Item pull-down menu to return a selected 
		attribute to the setting you used when you originally froze the attribute.
		This menu item will only be enabled if the attribute has a 
		frozen value and the current value deviates from that frozen value. 
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Changing Attribute Default Values
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
		Select an object or objects in the Preferences window.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click in any column in an attribute's row in the Preferences window
		to select it.
	</li>
			<li>
		Click on the Modify Selected Item in the Preferences toolbar
		and select an option from the pull-down menu. When you release
		the mouse button, the selected option will be applied to your
		object.
	</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/preferences_modify_menu.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
</vignette>
