<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Queries">
	<header1>
	Queries
	</header1>
		<bodytext>
			The file browser shows you files that meet certain criteria you specify in a <i>query</i>. Unlike a traditional directory listing, the files are not normally organized by <i>where</i> they are on your hard drive, but by more useful properties such as file type, name, or date. The file browser is more like a search engine than the Finder or Windows Explorer.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Searching for files by name
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			When searching for a file by name, you can start with an existing query and narrow down the results with the name you type, or you can search among all of your files.
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Choose the query you’d like start with by choosing a query from the Search For column. To search among all of your files, choose the <b>everything</b> query.
		</li>
		<li>
			Type all or part of the name you're looking for in the Search text field at the top of the file browser window.
			</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/file_browser15.png" />
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			As you type, results will appear that contain all or part of what you've typed.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
		<br /><space/>
	<bodytext>
		By entering text to use for searching, you've defined a new query. You can easily add other criteria to your search.
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Adding criteria to a query
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Click on the + button to the right of the main Search entry
			The search bar will expand to include a new search term. Click + to the right of the bottom search term to add additional criteria.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/file_browser8.png"  />
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<header2>
	Types of search criteria
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			<i>Author</i> lets you search for files by author.
		</li>
		<li>
			<i>Kind</i> lets you narrow your file search to a specific file type.
		</li>
		<li>
			<i>Last modified</i> provides various time frames to 
			constrain your search (yesterday, within last N days, etc.)
		</li>
		<li>
			<i>Name</i> menu narrows your search to files whose name begins or 
			ends with a search string.
		</li>
		<li>
			<i>Size</i> narrows your search by a file's size.
		</li>			
		<li>
			<i>Tag</i> narrows your search by a tag associated with a file.
		</li>			
		<li>
			<i>Text</i> will use the content of selected file types to narrow your search.
		</li>
		</ul>
	
<bluebox>
<header2>
Saving a query
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Click on the Save Search [+] button in the toolbar of the file browser window. The current query will be added to the List area, and its name is automatically selected for editing.
	</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
		The icon for your saved search is colored to indicate that it can be updated (the
		grey icons indicate that the search results are read-only and cannot be changed).
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/file_browser7.png"  />
	</bodytext>
</bluebox>
</vignette>
