<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Object Quickref">
	<header1>
	Object Quickref
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			Many Max objects will accept a variety of different kinds of messages. 
			While 
			<link module="core" name="assistance" type="vignette">Assistance</link>
			provides a very brief description of the most commonly used 
			messages to a Max object, you can get a list of <i>all</i> the messages 
			the object understands using the Quickref contextual menu. You can use the 
			Quickref menus as an aid to Max patching, automatically creating message
			boxes that contain messages to an object from the Quickref listing.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Viewing the Quickref pop-up menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>Click on any inlet to a Max object to show the Quickref pop-up menu.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/quickref_1.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
			The Quickref pop-up menu displays
		</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
			A listing of the messages the Max object accepts
		</li>
		<li>
			Menu items that let you open
			<link anchor="refman" module="core" name="help_docs" type="vignette">Reference pages</link>
			and
			<link module="core" name="help_docs" type="vignette">Help files</link>
			for the item.
		</li>
		<li>
			Menu items that let you send a message to the Max object without using a patch cord, and to query the output of the object
		</li>
	</ul>
	<bodytext>
			The Quickref menu gives you a short summary of each message and its syntax. The format of a Quickref listing is:
		</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>
			The name of the message
		</li>
		<li>
			The message type (int / float / symbol / array) for any additional messages [in square brackets]. If there the message is followed by a
			list, the number of items in the list is also shown in square brackets (e.g., <bi>color [float array[4]]</bi>  means that the object expects
			a message that begins with the symbol <i>color</i> and is followed by a list of 4 floats)
		</li>
		<li>
			The message’s default value, in parentheses (e.g. val = 0.73 0.82 0.63 1.00)
		</li>
	</ul>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Getting information from the Quickref pop-up menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>Click on the left inlet to a Max object to show the Quickref pop-up menu.
			As you move your cursor over any Quickref listing, a description of
			the message will appear in the
			Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Patching from the Quickref pop-up menu
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the left inlet to a Max object to show the Quickref pop-up menu
			and click on any message listed to select it. A <link name="message" type="refpage">message box</link> 
			containing the message connected to the left inlet of the Max object will 
			automatically be created, ready for you to complete by typing in any arguments the 
			message may require.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/quickref_2.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
