<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Scheduler Preferences">
	<header1>
	Scheduler Preferences
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			Max provides you with several options that allow you to fine-tune the Max application’s
			scheduler parameters to reflect your needs. You can adjust the rates at which the Max
			application updates the interface, choose to prioritize the handling of audio processing,
			and optimize the servicing of Max’s high and low-priority queues.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			With the exception of enabling or disabling Overdrive, most Max users will find that the
			default scheduler settings are sufficient for their use; these settings are provided for
			advanced users.
		</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
			Displaying Scheduler Preferences
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu (Macintosh) or the Options menu (Windows) to show the 
			<link module="core" name="preferences_window" type="vignette">Preferences Window</link>. 
			Scroll to the <b>Scheduler</b> category of the preferences listings.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/advanced_scheduler_settings.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Getting information about a Scheduler setting
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Move the mouse over the Setting column of any row in the Preferences window. A brief description of
			the setting will be shown in the
			Patcher window's 
			<link module="core" name="status_bar" type="vignette">Status Bar</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<header2>
	Overdrive
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			When <i>Overdrive</i> is enabled, Max gives priority to timing and MIDI processing
			over screen drawing and user interface tasks such as responding to mouse clicks.
			As a general rule: if you are primarily going to be using Max for MIDI or audio processing, Overdrive
			should be enabled. If you are primarily going to be using Jitter, Overdrive should be disabled. In addition, the debugging features of Max only work if overdrive is disabled.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Enabling/disabling Overdrive
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Choose <b>Overdrive</b> from the Options menu to toggle the current setting.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<header2>
	Advanced Scheduler Settings
</header2>
	<bodytext><link module="core" name="advanced_scheduler" type="vignette">Click here</link> to read about the more advanced scheduler and performance settings.
</bodytext>
</vignette>
