<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Sharing Patches">
	<header1>
	Sharing Patches
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
Max patcher files are in a text-based format, so they are easy to share. You can copy all or part of a patcher to the clipboard, then paste it into an e-mail message. You can also receive e-mail messages with patchers, copy them to the clipboard, and paste them into Max.
</bodytext>
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Copying a patcher into an e-mail message
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>If you want to send e-mail with part of a patcher, select the objects you want to include. If you want to include all objects, choose <b>Select All</b> from the Edit menu.</li>
		<li>Choose <b>Copy</b> from the Edit menu to copy the selected objects to the clipboard</li>
		<li>Switch to your e-mail client. Paste the contents of the clipboard into a message</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Copying a patcher into an e-mail message in compressed format
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		Max offers a compressed text format for copying patcher data to the clipboard. This may be useful when posting excerpts of a patcher on a public forum or mailing list. The text is "unreadable" but will be a small fraction the size of the usual text format. 
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>Select the part of the patch you wish to copy</li>
		<li>Choose <b>Copy Compressed</b> from the Edit menu to copy the selected objects to the clipboard</li>
		<li>Switch to your e-mail client. Paste the contents of the clipboard into a message</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
<bluebox>
	<header2>
		Opening a patcher from an e-mail message
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
		Max can create objects from text on the clipboard in the old Max 4 text format, standard Max format, 
		or the compressed format.
	</bodytext>
	<ul>
		<li>Because there may be a lot of text involved in the patcher data, the easiest technique for selecting all 
		of the data is select a line at the beginning of the text, then scroll to the end of the message and Shift-click 
		to select the end of the text.</li>
		<li>Once all of the text is selected, choose <b>Copy</b> from the Edit menu in your e-mail client. If you are
		manually selecting all the data, be sure to include the <i>begin_max5_patcher</i> and <i>end_max5_patcher</i> 
		lines in their entirety.</li>
		<li>Switch to Max.</li>
		<li>If you want to create a new patcher window with the patcher data you've received, choose <b>New From Clipboard</b> from the File menu. A new patcher window will appear with the objects from the e-mail message.</li>
		<li>If you want to paste the objects in the e-mail message into an existing unlocked patcher, choose <b>Paste</b> from the Edit menu.</li>
		
	</ul>
</bluebox>
</vignette>
