<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="shortcuts">
	<header1>
	Shortcuts
	</header1>
	<header2>
	Window management
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Command-click (Macintosh) or Control-click (Windows) in any white space to lock or
			unlock the Patcher window (if it is editable).
		</li>
		<li>
			Option-click (Macintosh) or Alt-click (Windows) on a window's close box to close
			all windows except the Max window.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Working with the Object Explorer
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			You can use the up/down/left/right arrow keys to move horizontally 
			or vertically among icons and category tabs in the 
			<link module="core" name="object_explorer" type="vignette">Object Explorer</link>.
		</li>
		<li>
			Double-clicking on a selected object will create and instance of the object
			in the center of your patcher window.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Selecting a patch cord or objects and patch cords
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Option-drag (Macintosh) or Alt-drag (Windows) a rectangle around a patch
			cord or set of patch cords and objects to select all the objects and patch
			cords in the area you drag over.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Moving Max objects in the Patcher window
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Click on any object in an unlocked Patcher window to select it, and hold down
			the Shift key while dragging the object. The selected object will be constrained
			to move in only horizontally or vertically. If the object being dragged is connected to another object, shift-dragging will snap the object when the connection between the two objects is vertical.
		</li>
		<li>
			Click on any object in an unlocked Patcher window to select it. Use the arrow keys
			to move a selected object will move in any direction by 1 pixel or the default value
			if you have chosen Snap To Grid from the Options menu.
		</li>
		<li>
			To temporarily disable alignment guides and Snap to Grid when moving objects,
			click on any object(s) in an unlocked Patcher window to select and hold down
			the Command key (Macintosh) or Control key (Windows) while dragging the object(s).
		</li>
		</ul>
	<header2>
	Duplicating objects
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Click on any object in an unlocked Patcher window to select them, then
			Option-click (Macintosh) or Alt-click (Windows) on the object and drag to
			duplicate the object.
		</li>
		<li>
			Immediately after duplicating an object by choosing <b>Duplicate</b> from the Edit menu, you can use the mouse to move the duplicated object in any
			direction from the original. Subsequent <b>Duplicate</b> commands will distribute the new objects with the same spacing.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Using user interface objects in an unlocked Patcher window
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Hold down the Command (Macintosh) or Control (Windows) key while clicking
			on a user interface object (such as a number box, slider, or toggle). The
			object will behave as though the Patcher window were locked (i.e. you can
			toggle switches, set numbers, move faders, etc.).
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Presentation Mode shortcuts
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Option-command-E (Macintosh) or Alt-control-E (Windows) will
			toggle between Patching and Presentation Modes.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Viewing help files and reference pages
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Option-click (Macintosh) or Alt-click (Windows) on 
			an object box in an unlocked Patcher window to view an object’s help file.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Object editing shortcuts
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Hold down the Command (Macintosh) key or Control (Windows) key and
			double-click on any <o>coll</o> or <o>table</o> object or subpatcher
			in any unlocked patcher window to view its contents.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Inspector shortcuts
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Position your cursor on the left edge of the object, and use the
			<link module="core" name="circular_object_menu" type="vignette">Circular object menu</link>
			when it appears to show the object Inspector.
		</li>
		<li>
			You can select rows of the inspector with the up and down arrow keys, or type the first few letters of an attribute name to move to that row. Once a row has been selected, pressing the Return key will start editing the text of the attribute.
		</li>
		<li>
			The Cut, Copy, and Paste keyboard shortcuts using the Command keys (Macintosh)
			or the Control keys (Windows) work in the text fields of any object's Inspector window.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<header2>
	Finding all instances of a send, receive or value object
	</header2>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Double-click on a  <o>send</o>, <o>receive</o>, or <o>value</o> object
			to show a contextual menu that lists of all instances of these objects,
			followed by the name of the patcher windows in which they are used. When you choose the desired instance from the menu, the patcher window will be opened (if necessary) and the object will be highlighted.
		</li>
	</ul>
</vignette>
