<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Mac Standalone Applications">
	<header1>
	Mac Platform Information for Standalone Applications
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
		Max builds universal binary standalone applications on the Mac. The standalone is an <i>application package</i>, which is also a folder that looks like a file in the Finder. Double-clicking on the file's icon launches the application.
	</bodytext>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Examining the contents of a Mac standalone
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Control-click on the standalone application and choose <b>Show Package Contents</b> from the contextual menu. A new Finder window will open showing the contents of the package.
	</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
<br />
	<bodytext>
		YourApplication.app [ note: the .app is not shown in the Finder ]
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab />Contents [ folder ]
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab />Frameworks [ folder ] – needed for external object support
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab />Info.plist [ copied from your Info.plist if included in a collective build script ]
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab />YourApplication.mxf [ collective containing your patches ]
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab />MacOS [ folder ]
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab /><tab />YourApplication [ actually the Max Runtime executable ]
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab />support [ folder ] – audio and MIDI support files
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab />Resources [ folder ]
	</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<tab /><tab /><tab />[ custom icon file goes here ]
	</bodytext>

<bluebox>
<header2>
Including Jitter shader components in your Mac standalone application
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Build your application without including any shaders or frameworks in
		the build script.
	</li>
	<li>
		The <i>Cg.framework</i> is copied to your standalone automatically if you use either the <o>jit.gl.shader</o> or the <o>jit.gl.slab</o> object.
	</li>
	<li>
		Copy the <i>jitter-shaders</i> folder from the Cycling '74 folder inside the Max
		application folder to <i>{Package}/Contents/MacOS/support/jitter-shaders</i>.
		Be sure to include any
		shader files that the included shaders use. Many of the included 
		image-processing shaders rely on one of the "passthru" vertex shader programs 
		that reside in the <i>shared</i> 
		folder inside the <i>jitter-shaders</i> folder.
	</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
		<br /><space/>
<bluebox>
<header2>
Including Java components in your Macintosh standalone application
</header2>
	<ul>
	<li>
		Copy the file <i>java/lib/max.jar</i> from the Cycling '74 folder inside the Max application folder to <i>{Package}/Contents/support/java/lib/max.jar</i>
	</li>
	<li>
		Copy any other necessary jar files (e.g., jitter.jar) to <i>{Package}/Contents/support/java/lib/</i>
	</li>
	<li>
		Copy any necessary class files from <i>java/classes/*.class</i> in the Cycling '74 folder to <i>{Package}/Contents/support/java/classes/*.class</i>.
	</li>
	</ul>
</bluebox>
		<br /><space/>
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Adding a custom icon for a Macintosh standalone application
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Create a line with the <b>appicon</b> script keyword in your standalone's build script followed by the full pathname of an icon file you’ve created with
			Apple's Icon Composer tool or another application that creates these files. This will copy the icon file into the standalone application package's Resources folder.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			In some cases, you may need to log out and log back in again before the standalone’s icon will show up.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br />
</vignette>
