<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Text Entry">
	<header1>
	Entering text and special characters in Max
	</header1>
		<bodytext>
			Max lets you enter certain "special" characters into a max object
			box (such as <o>sprintf</o>) or a <o>message</o> box more easily.
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
		<li>
			In earlier versions of Max, quotes were considered to be <i>part of a symbol</i> if the string contained no
			spaces, and quotation marks were ignored otherwise, as shown:
			<br />
			<img src="images/text_entry_1.png"  />
			<br />
			<br />
			Now, when you type <m>"hello"</m> in a <o>message</o> box, the text will automatically change to read
			<m>hello</m> (note the lack of quotation marks) to make it clear that the quotes are not really 
			part of the symbol. 
		</li>
		<li>
			Previously, anything typed between a pair of quotation marks was parsed by the
			Max application; If you wanted to include characters like commas or semicolons,
			you needed to add a backslash ( \ ) before the character to escape them.
			<br />
			<br />
			Now, you can type commas and semicolons into a <o>message</o> box without any 
			difficulty - if you forget and accidentally type the old school character 
			string <m>"one\, two\, three"</m>  (i.e. note the quotations and the backslash-escaped 
			commas) into a <o>message</o> box, it will automatically be converted into <m>"one, two, three"</m>.
		</li>
		<li>
			In earlier versions of Max, there never was a good way to deal with a quotation mark
			between a pair of quotation marks - the escape character would vanish when you 
			duplicated the object (i.e. <m>"oh #$\"^%"</m> would change to <m>"oh #$"^%"</m> 
			as soon as you copied it.
			<br />
			<br />
			If you want to include a quotation mark in a symbol in Max, you can use a backslash
			character to escape it, and it will be retained when you copy the object.
			<br />
			<br />
			If you want to include a backslash character in a symbol, you can escape it by adding a
			second backslash.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			All Max objects and message boxes use the same rules - If you want to type a comma or semicolon,
			it must be escaped or quoted. This is true regardless of whether or not the comma or semicolon
			is enclosed in quotation marks.
		</bodytext>
	
	<header2>
		Special characters in older (imported) Max patches
	</header2>
		<bodytext>
			When you open a patch created with an earlier version of Max and import it, Max will
			change the contents of the message or object box to reflect the old way of doing
			things in order to remind you of your original intent.
			
			automatically convert escaped text into quoted text; If it is not quoted or escaped,
			the it works just as it did with earlier versions of Max.
		</bodytext>	
		<ul>
		<li>
			When you import an old patch containing the character string <m>"hello"</m> (i.e., something in
			quotations with no spaces), the <o>message</o> box will appear in Max as <m>\"hello\"</m> 
			(with the quotation marks present and escaped with backslashes to indicate that the quotes in the
			original patch were a part of the symbol.
		</li>
		<li>
			When you import an old patch with a <o>message</o> box containing the character string <m>one\, two\, three</m>
			will appear in Max as a message box containing the character string <m>"one," "two," "three"</m>.
		</li>
		</ul>
</vignette>
