<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Patches in Text Format">
	<header1>
	Patches in Text Format
	</header1>
		<bodytext>
			The most convenient way to exchange Max patches with others is to convert them to
			text files which can be emailed more easily than trying to send patches as email
			attachments or creating StuffIt files. Max lets you convert an entire patch or
			a portion of one to a text file, and to convert Max patches saved in text format to visual patches automatically.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			You can exchange Max patches in text format between Macintosh and Windows machines. If a
			text format Max patch contains a third-party Max object or an abstraction you don't have on
			your system, you'll see an error message in the Max window
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/text_patches1.png"  />
		</bodytext>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			and the Max object will be differently colored, although it will appear with the correct
			number of inlets and outlets.
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/text_patches2.png"  />
		</bodytext>
		</bodytext>
		<bodytext>
			If someone sends you a Max patch with a user interface they have created using
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="presentation_mode">Presentation Mode</link>
			and
			they have set the patch to open in Presentation mode, you'll see the user interface when you convert the file.
			To edit the patch, switch to Patcher mode by clicking on the Presentation Mode icon in the Patcher Window toolbar.
		</bodytext>
	<br />
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Saving a finished patch as text
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Choose <b>Open As Text...</b> from the File menu and use the file dialog box to select your file.
			A new text window will open that contains the file you have selected in text form. Choose
			<b>Select All</b> from the Edit menu to select the text, then choose <b>Copy</b> from the Edit
			menu to copy the text to the clipboard. You can paste this text into an email or a text file to
			share with others. Note that if your patcher contains any
			abstractions, you will need to
			open and save them separately.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
		<br /><space/><bluebox>
	<header2>
	Saving a Max patch in Text format
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Choose <b>Save As...</b> from the Edit menu, and then chose Max text file from the Format
			pop-up menu in the file dialog. The file will be saved as a Max text file (<i>.mxt</i>).
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
		<br /><space/>
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Saving a portion of a patch as text
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Select the patch or portion of a patch you wish to save as text.
			Choose <b>Copy</b> from the Edit menu to copy the selected portion to the clipboard.
			Open a text editor or email client and paste the contents of the clipboard into a
			new document.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
		<br /><space/>
	<bluebox>
	<header2>
	Converting a text file to a Max patch
	</header2>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Select the textfile or portion of an email that contains the Max patch. Be sure that you copy the
			entire file, which begins and ends with a single curly bracket ( {/} ) as the very first character
			on a line. Copy the selected portion to the clipboard. Choose <b>New From Clipboard</b> from the File menu,
			and a new Patcher window will be instantiated, and the pasted-in text will appear as a Max patch.
		<br />
			<b>Note:</b> Max uses the 
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="unicode">Unicode format</link>.
			which means that email clients 
			that don't support Unicode (such as Eudora) won't allow for simple copying and 
			pasting from the clipboard. If you copy a Max patch and it doesn't paste into 
			your email client as a text file,
			<link type="vignette" module="core" name="sharing_patches" anchor="unicodecopypaste">click here for some helpful advice</link>.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
			
</vignette>
