<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Object Defaults">
	<header1>
	Object Defaults
	</header1>
	<bodytext>
			When you launch Max, the colors for all Max objects are set to
			default values. You can change the look of individual objects using the
			object's
			<link module="core" name="inspector" type="vignette">Inspector</link>,
			and you can use the
			<link module="core" name="patcher_inspector" type="vignette">Patcher Inspector</link>
			to set the background color for a patcher window in both its locked and unlocked states.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Max also allows you to change the default settings of a large number of
			Max objects using the Object Defaults window. These object default settings 
			are recalled each time you launch Max. You can use the Object Defaults window 
			to customize the look of your copy of Max, and to maintain a consistent look 
			across Max patches.
			<br/>
			<b>Note:</b> Although the Object Defaults window lists a large number
			of default preferences for Max objects, it does not list them all. You can
			use the
			<link module="core" name="prototypes" type="vignette">object prototype</link>
			feature to create customized versions of any UI objects not listed in the 
			Object Defaults window and maintain a consistent look to your
			patches.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<header2>
	The Object Defaults Window
	</header2>
	<bodytext>
			The Object Defaults Window includes of a set of tabs you can use to change what
			is displayed in the window, and a listing of all the settings associated
			with all Max objects.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
		<img src="images/ui_defaults1.png"/>
	</bodytext>
	<header2>
	Object Defaults Tabs
	</header2>
	<bodytext><i>All</i> shows the settings for all objects.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext><i>Patcher</i> shows features associated with the Patcher window,
			such as background and patch cord colors.
		</bodytext>
	<bodytext>
			Object-specific settings are found under the tabs identified with 
			icons as seen in the Object Explorer. Move the mouse over a tab to 
			see the object's name.
		</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Changing a default value for an object
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>Select the desired object's tab at the top of the Object Defaults window</li>
			<li>
			Click in the Value column for a setting you want to change. Use the pop-up 
			<link module="core" name="color_picker" type="vignette">Color Picker</link> 
			to change the color.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bodytext>
			As you change a color, you'll notice that it will change in any open 
			patcher windows containing the object whose defaults you are modifying.
		</bodytext>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Restoring default values
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click on the x at the bottom of the windows to restore default values.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/ui_defaults6.png"/>
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Saving a set of object defaults
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click the <b>Save Settings</b>
			button in Object Defaults window toolbar. Type a name for the settings file. Click OK.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			Your new color set will be added to the pop-up menu you see when you
			click on the <b>Load Settings</b> button.
		</bodytext>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Loading a set of object defaults
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click the <b>Load Settings</b> button in the Object Defaults window toolbar
			and choose a settings file from the menu.
		</li>
		</ul>
		<bodytext>
			<img src="images/ui_defaults5.png"/>
		</bodytext>
		<ul>
			<li>
			The chosen settings will be loaded, the Object Defaults window will show
			the new colors, and the color set will be applied to all open patcher windows. 
			It will also be used in any newly created patcher windows as well as become the 
			default color set the next time you launch Max.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
	Reverting to the default object colors
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Click the Set All to Default Values button in the Object Window toolbar. All 
			colors of all objects will be restored to their original default values.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
	<br/>
	<space/>
	<bodytext>
		Normally, when you save a patch, the current default colors are not stored. 
		Instead, no value is stored for a color if it is set to the default value. 
		This has the effect of making files smaller as well as making it possible 
		to apply your default colors not just to new patches, but to patches you 
		made in the past or patches you get from other people. However, if you 
		really want specific colors in a patch, you can save all object attributes, 
		whether they are set to the current default value or not. 
	</bodytext>
	<bluebox>
		<header2>
		Insulating a patch from the effect of object defaults
	</header2>
		<ul>
			<li>Before saving a patcher, choose Patcher Inspector from the View 
		menu to open the patcher inspector window.</li>
			<li>Check Save Default-Valued Object Attributes.</li>
			<li>Close the patcher inspector window and save the patcher.</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
</vignette>
