<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<vignette name="Unicode Conversion">
		<header1>
			Converting Max 4 Patches to Unicode
		</header1>
  		<bodytext>
			If you have only created Max patches with Roman characters A-Z etc. you 
			probably don't have to worry about the specifics of the text encoding 
			conversion process that Max needs to use in order to open older documents. 
			However, if you (for example) used accents on Roman characters, or added 
			comments in Japanese to your patches, the information below may be helpful.
  		</bodytext>
		<header2>
			Converting older Max documents on the Macintosh
		</header2>
  		<bodytext>
			Before Unicode was widely adopted, the Mac OS used a system of encoding 
			text in a font-specific way. For example, if you wrote text in Helvetica, 
			it was stored in the Macroman encoding. Macroman is an eight-bit encoding 
			that specifies how a limited set of extended characters are stored, but it 
			does not handle, say, Japanese characters. If you used the Osaka font, the 
			Mac OS would store text using the Shift-JIS encoding. This means that in an 
			older Max patch created on the Mac, there might be several different 
			encodings based on the font that was used.
		</bodytext>  
  		<bodytext>
			Since Max only works with Unicode, any text encoding used in an old Max 
			document must be recognized and converted. Max assumes that all pre-Max 5 
			documents are encoded in Macroman. However, Max can be configured to 
			recognize font-specific text encodings on the Mac when importing older
			documents using two settings in the 
			Preferences Window.
		</bodytext> 
		<br /><space />
	<bluebox>
  		<header2>
  			Enabling font-specific text encoding detection (Macintosh only)
  		</header2>
  		<ul>
		<li>
 			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Max menu to show the Preferences Window. 
			Click the <b>Font</b> tab to show the Font preferences.
		</li>
		<li>
			Click in the Attempt Text Encoding Conversion checkbox to set the preference.
			<br />
			Check the Two Byte Comment Import Encoding attribute setting to be sure 
			it is set to Autodetect. If not, choose Autodetect from the pop-up menu to
			select it.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
<br /><space />
  		<bodytext>
			The Attempt Text Encoding Conversion examines the font for each 
			bit of text as a file is being imported to see if it specifies a text 
			encoding other than Macroman. If so, it performs a special conversion 
			of the text to Unicode using the encoding specified by the font. This 
			option is turned off by default to improve the speed of importing patches. 
			It should be noted that text encodings other than Macroman were not 
			officially supported in previous versions of Max for anything other 
			than comment objects in two-byte-compatible mode. However, using the 
			Macintosh's font-specific encoding technique, non-Macroman encodings 
			often worked, and this option permits some success in recovering the 
			information when importing a patch that used this capability. Note 
			that the font used in the original document must be present on the 
			system in order for the correct original encoding to be detected.
		</bodytext>
  		<bodytext>
			Two Byte Comment Import Encoding uses a similar technique to recover the 
			original text encoding. You can turn the font-based detection feature off 
			by choosing Macroman for this setting. If you are importing a document 
			that contains text you know is encoded in Shift-JIS but may use Japanese 
			fonts you do not have, you can choose Shift-JI force the comment text to be 
			treated as if it were in this encoding.
		</bodytext>		
		<header2>
			Converting older Max Documents on Windows
		</header2>
  		<bodytext>
			Older versions of Max that ran on Windows systems did not have the 
			ability to store text using encodings specific to a particular font. 
			By and large, Max documents were encoded in Macroman. If you have 
			older Max documents originally created on the Mac that you are trying 
			to open on Windows, you may not be able to see the text properly, 
			as there is no way for Windows to map font names (which are probably 
			Macintosh-specific in the first place) to text encodings. If the Macintosh 
			user was smart enough to use two-byte comments, you may be able to recover 
			Shift-JIS encoded text.
		</bodytext>
		<br /><space />
	<bluebox>
  		<header2>
  			Recovering Shift-JIS encoded text (Windows only)
  		</header2>
  		<ul>
		<li>
 			Choose <b>Preferences</b> from the Options menu to show the Preferences Window. 
			Click the <b>Font</b> tab to show the Font preferences.
		</li>
		<li>
			Click in the Value column for the Two Byte Comment Import Encoding setting
			and choose Shift-JIS from the pop-up menu.
		</li>
		</ul>
	</bluebox>
<br /><space />

</vignette>
